<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Foneros on Andrea Grandi</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/tags/foneros/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Foneros on Andrea Grandi</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.andreagrandi.it/tags/foneros/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Fon: how long are you going to play tricks on users?</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/fon-how-long-are-you-going-to-play-tricks-on-users/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/fon-how-long-are-you-going-to-play-tricks-on-users/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/fon-how-long-are-you-going-to-play-tricks-on-users/fon-300x294.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;300&#34;
	height=&#34;294&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;fon&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;102&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;244px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As many of you already know, &lt;strong&gt;Fon&lt;/strong&gt; is a spanish company that some years ago had the
interesting idea of creating a &lt;strong&gt;wifi community&lt;/strong&gt; to share the Internet
connection. The idea is quite simple: each &amp;ldquo;fonero&amp;rdquo; buy a Fonera (the
router sold by Fon), register it on the Fon system and get a
username/password. If the fonero travels around the world he&amp;rsquo;s able to
connect to wifi signal of other foneras and browse the web for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I bought my first fonera few years ago, I was one of the first
people in my city. I bought it because I was really beliving in this
project. During these years Fon produced new models of fonera and I
bought each of them (the WRT54 router, Fonera, Fonera+, Fonera 2.0g,
Fonera 2.0n ecc&amp;hellip;.). Since first year, the Fon community has grown a
lot and now there are a lot of foneros around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;## Actual situation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few months ago Fon launched a very interesting product: &lt;strong&gt;Fonera 2.0g&lt;/strong&gt;.
Thats&amp;rsquo;s not only a router. Fonera 2 is capable of managing torrents,
rapidshare downloads, uploading photo on Facebook and Flickr, and much
more. Whats&amp;rsquo;s wrong with this product? It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;very unstable&lt;/strong&gt;! There are
a lot of users that bought this router when it was anounced and they&amp;rsquo;re
still waiting for a lot of bugs to be fixed by Fon developers team
(composed by only ONE person!). Why users had to wait so long?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple! They were working to Fonera 2.0n! Wow! Faster router, more RAM,
4 ethernet port, wonderful! But&amp;hellip; another very unstable router! And
with unstable I mean: it &lt;strong&gt;disconnects/reboots often&lt;/strong&gt;, connection is
unstable, applications don&amp;rsquo;t work ecc&amp;hellip;. I&amp;rsquo;m talking about a 79€
router, not about something that users had as preview product. Me and
other users were still waiting for an uograde when&amp;hellip; Fon &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://english.martinvarsavsky.net/general/fon-to-unveil-new-fonera-at-mobile-world-congress.html&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;announced a new product&lt;/a&gt;!
Yes, another one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fon priority is not to fix a product that thousand of users have already
bought. Fon priority is to produce and sell a new product!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could be only my opinion, but I don&amp;rsquo;t trust you anymore Fon! I&amp;rsquo;m
really disappointed about your behaviour you had with your customers.
I&amp;rsquo;ve already spent (wasted) a lot of money with your not-working
products and I&amp;rsquo;m not going to buy your products anymore! I&amp;rsquo;m tired of
being illuded by your promises: how long are you going to play tricks on
users?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
