<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Summit on Andrea Grandi</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/tags/summit/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Summit on Andrea Grandi</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.andreagrandi.it/tags/summit/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>UDS day-0</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/uds-day-0/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/uds-day-0/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/uds-day-0/IMG_0254-300x200.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;300&#34;
	height=&#34;200&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;uds&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;150&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;360px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I left from &lt;strong&gt;Firenze&lt;/strong&gt; with my friend &lt;strong&gt;Marco Trevisan&lt;/strong&gt;, to go to
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://uds.ubuntu.com&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Ubuntu Developer Summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;Budapest&lt;/strong&gt;. We
changed flight in &lt;strong&gt;Rome&lt;/strong&gt; where we met also &lt;strong&gt;Andrea Azzarone&lt;/strong&gt;.
Unluckly &lt;strong&gt;Alitalia losts Marco&amp;rsquo;s baggage&lt;/strong&gt;, so he&amp;rsquo;s still waiting for
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrived at the hotel at 20:00 more or less where we met other people
of the community. There are &lt;strong&gt;lot of italians&lt;/strong&gt; at UDS. Most work for
Canonical, other were sponsored by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I met &lt;strong&gt;Marianna Raffaele&lt;/strong&gt; (one of the UDS organizer&amp;hellip; yeah, she&amp;rsquo;s
italian too!), I had to explain her a little problem I had with my
booking (nothing bad) and she managed to help me. She also gave me a
very nice guitar plettre with Ubuntu logo. Thank you Marianna for this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We went out with &lt;strong&gt;Jorge Castro&lt;/strong&gt; to drink some beers (he offered me
one, thanks Jorge!!!) and we met lot of other Ubuntu people. A really
amazing start!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>UDS day-2</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/uds-day-2/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/uds-day-2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/uds-day-2/IMG_0323-300x200.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;300&#34;
	height=&#34;200&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;uds&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;150&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;360px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This day at UDS started a bit late for me, since i woke up pretty sick (damn
air conditioned!!!). I did not follow any conferences in the morning. I
relly wanted to follow the &lt;strong&gt;Wayland&lt;/strong&gt; one, but when I arrived the room
was already full and it was almost impossible to enter, so I decided not
to enter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I attended &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s wrong with UDS and how we can fix it&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; session
before having lunch. We discussed the possibility to improve all the
session in general, for example giving them a proper order so that a
team can first discuss some API interface, then another team can discuss
how to design them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had another wonderful and tasty &lt;strong&gt;lunch&lt;/strong&gt;, even if I didn&amp;rsquo;t eat so
much, but food was very good anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the afternoon I followed an interesting track: &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Recommend music
based on current song playing or on users media library&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;. We discussed
the possibilities to implement a music suggestion service, based on
user&amp;rsquo;s tastes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent the rest of theconference time writing these blog posts and
uploading pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the sessions we had the &lt;strong&gt;Linaro Showcase&lt;/strong&gt;: lot of demo running
on Linaro and ARM processors. I was really impressed by a robot with
Kinect that was able to follow people recognizing their faces. During
the showcase there was a very nice dinner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After dinner I went out with my friend &lt;strong&gt;Manrique Lopez&lt;/strong&gt; who is here in
Budapest for another conference, so we decided to meet for a good beer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before coming back to the hotel me, &lt;strong&gt;Marco Trevisan&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Andrea
Azzarone&lt;/strong&gt; had a nice talk with &lt;strong&gt;Jorge Castro&lt;/strong&gt;. He really make us feel
part of the Ubuntu family!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>UDS day-3</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/uds-day-3/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/uds-day-3/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/uds-day-3/IMG_0260-300x200.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;300&#34;
	height=&#34;200&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;uds&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;150&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;360px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even this morning I didn&amp;rsquo;t wake up early because I still felt sick (I already
know this sore throath won&amp;rsquo;t abandon me untile I go back home).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a &lt;strong&gt;light breakfast at 10:30&lt;/strong&gt; and then I finishes uploading some
pictures and published articles on my blog I already had written before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While waiting to attend a session, I found &lt;strong&gt;Mark Shuttleworth&lt;/strong&gt; around
and I congratulated with him for the effort he is putting into Ubuntu.
Without a similar distribution, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure that Linux would not be
so popular today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had lunch at 13:00 as usual and after that I attended a couple of
presentation. The first one on Eucalyptus, then &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Cooking Recipes&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;
for Ubuntu and another one dedicated to &lt;strong&gt;Wine&lt;/strong&gt;. The Wine session was
so funny! They had a little problem with video projector and all the
images appeared with a blur effect so that you could think to be drunk
;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After these sessions I had to go back to my room since I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel
very well, but I was able to attend &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Unity&amp;rsquo;s relations and
dependancies on GNOME&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; thanks to audio streaming, IRC for asking
questions and etherpad to take notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I attended also &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;desktop-dx-o-unity-a11y&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; where there was a
discussion about the state of &lt;strong&gt;Unity&lt;/strong&gt; and what can be improved before
&lt;strong&gt;Oneiric&lt;/strong&gt; release. Lot of work has to be done yet, in particular about
accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last session of this day, a
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://summit.ubuntu.com/uds-o/meeting/other-o-sabdfl-community-qa/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Q+A&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
with &lt;strong&gt;Mark Shuttleworth&lt;/strong&gt;. The session was very interesting! He replied
to all questions coming from the public and from IRC.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Giving Lightning Talks</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/giving-lightning-talks/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/giving-lightning-talks/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/giving-lightning-talks/lightning.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;709&#34;
	height=&#34;1001&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;lightning&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;70&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;169px&#34;
	
&gt;{ width=20% }&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During next &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://wiki.maemo.org/Maemo_Summit_2009&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maemo Summit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; we will have at least
2 hours (one on saturday and another one on sunday) of lightning talks,
about 20 talks where people will try to explain or present something in
just &lt;strong&gt;5 minutes&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, during Maemo Summit 2008, I did a lightning talk too and I
must admit: even if I knew a lot about the subject of my talk and even
if I had already done many other talks, I think it wasn&amp;rsquo;t so good as I
expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I&amp;rsquo;ve been selected again (more details will follow) to give a
5 minutes talk and with this great news the kind &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://maemo.org/profile/view/dneary&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dave Neary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; also suggested me a
&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.perl.com/pub/a/2004/07/30/lightningtalk.html&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;link&lt;/a&gt; with an
article about some best practices when giving lightning talks. I&amp;rsquo;ll try
to resume the most important points, hoping this will be useful for
people who is going to give a short presentation at Summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;go-straight-to-the-point&#34;&gt;Go straight to the point
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Five minutes finish sooner than you can
expect. You have to talk about the main topic of your talk within the
two first minutes, else you risk to talk too much about the rest and you
couldn&amp;rsquo;t have the time for the most important thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;leave-details-away&#34;&gt;Leave details away
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;People will never remember too many details
explained in so little time. It&amp;rsquo;s better to leave them away and put them
in a more detailed blog post that you can link within your slides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;slides&#34;&gt;Slides
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a five minute talk you can avoid preparing slides, but
if this can help you to concentrate on points you have to talk about,
please prepare them. Two or three slides can be useful to introduce
yourself, to write any reference of what you&amp;rsquo;re talking about many other
things. Another important thing, make sure your slides are ready before
starting your presentation: people don&amp;rsquo;t want to wait 20-30 seconds it
takes to start Open Office or any other similar application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;consider-any-eventuality&#34;&gt;Consider any eventuality
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The presentation file could be damaged (be
sure to have a copy of it, better in PDF format), your laptop could have
no more battery (make sure you&amp;rsquo;ve a copy of your slides in a USB key),
aliens could take you away, ecc&amp;hellip; (ok, this last eventuality is
remote).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;concluding-your-talk&#34;&gt;Concluding your talk
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t worry if you finish one or two minutes
before, people won&amp;rsquo;t bother about it. It&amp;rsquo;s better to finish one minute
before than 30 seconds later. If you want to leave an URL where people
can find more details, how to contact you, put it in every slide so
people will be able to take note of it from the first minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to have resumed the most important points of the &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.perl.com/pub/a/2004/07/30/lightningtalk.html&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;original article&lt;/a&gt;.
If you think there are any other important things to say, please leave me a
comment and I&amp;rsquo;ll add them. I really hope you will enjoy Maemo Summit and
its lightning talks!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Registration to Maemo Summit 2009 open!</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/registration-to-maemo-summit-2009-open/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/registration-to-maemo-summit-2009-open/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/registration-to-maemo-summit-2009-open/Maemo_org_logo_colour.png&#34;
	width=&#34;592&#34;
	height=&#34;143&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;Maemo Logo&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;413&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;993px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://maemo.org/news/events/registrations/register/e840196271eb11deb15535a00f6d72187218&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Registration&lt;/a&gt;
for the &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://wiki.maemo.org/Maemo_Summit_2009&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Maemo Summit 2009&lt;/a&gt; has
been opened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The summit will have free entrance, but registration is required to
grant you food, drinks, a maemo.org shirt and a seat. Please register as
soon as possible, so we can get a clear picture of how many people are
expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://maemo.org/news/events/registrations/register/e840196271eb11deb15535a00f6d72187218&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;The registration form&lt;/a&gt;
also has an option for sponsorship requests. Details about sponsorship
will be published later and requests will be evaluated after this. You
can always change your registration entry at a later point in time if
needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event location details and a list of participants can be found
&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://maemo.org/news/events/maemo_summit_2009/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you all in Amsterdam at Maemo Summit 2009!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Maemo Summit (Berlino) - giorno 2</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/maemo-summit-berlino-giorno-2/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/maemo-summit-berlino-giorno-2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wiki.maemo.org/images/9/9c/MaemoSummit091908.jpg&#34;
	
	
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;Maemo Summit&#34;
	
	
&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Con circa 30 minuti di ritardo (maledetto stinco di maiale della sera
prima!) arriviamo al &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.c-base.org/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;C-base&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. La sede del
C-base è veramente straordinaria: costruita sulle fondamenta di un
vecchio edificio lungo le rive del fiume, ha al suo interno ben due bar,
tre sale conferenza, e tantissime altre stanze dove vengono fatte altre
attività (una scuola di musica, una scuola di ballo ecc&amp;hellip;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dopo aver ritirato i nostri badge, ci accomodiamo nella sala principale
dove &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://maemo.org/profile/view/jaaksi/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ari Jaaksi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, il
vice-presidente di &lt;strong&gt;Nokia&lt;/strong&gt;, sta tenendo il talk introduttivo della
giornata. La sala è stracolma di persone e siamo quindi costretti a
sistemarci in piedi in fondo alla sala.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Il talk successivo è a cura di &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://dailythemes.wordpress.com/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jay Sullivan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, sviluppatore di del team
di &lt;strong&gt;Mozilla&lt;/strong&gt;. Non vengono annunciate particolari novità, il talk che
seguirà sarà molto piu&amp;rsquo; interessante.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Harri Kiljander&lt;/strong&gt; di &lt;strong&gt;Nokia&lt;/strong&gt; ci presenta alcune delle novità che
saranno presenti in &lt;strong&gt;Maemo 5&lt;/strong&gt; e nei futuri device. Tra le cose piu&#39;
importanti che vengono messe in risalto, ci sarà finalmente il supporto
per il &lt;strong&gt;multi touch&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dopo un altro paio di talk ed una breve pausa per riorganizzare le idee,
arriva il momento tanto temuto: quello di tenere il talk! Il motivo per
cui sono andato al Summit infatti era per tenere un talk (seppur breve)
su due plugin (&lt;strong&gt;Pluthon&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ESBox&lt;/strong&gt;) per &lt;strong&gt;Eclipse&lt;/strong&gt; che vengono
utilizzati per sviluppare applicazione per Maemo. Nei cinque minuti
messi a disposizione, riesco per fortuna a dire quelle poche cose che mi
ero &amp;ldquo;preparato&amp;rdquo;. Onestamente non avevo preparato però alcuna slide, e
questo non mi è stato di grande aiuto. Ho pensato subito che se avessi
avuto con me anche 5 o 6 slide che sintetizzavano quello che avrei
dovuto dire, sarebbe stato tutto molto piu&amp;rsquo; facile. Oltretutto il talk
doveva essere in inglese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://wiki.maemo.org/images/7/7d/MaemoSummit_catering.jpg&#34;
	
	
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;Maemo Summit - catering&#34;
	
	
&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finalmente arriva l&amp;rsquo;ora di pranzo. Veniamo tutti dirottati in una sala al piano
terra dove gli organizzatori hanno fatto arrivare vassoi di crostini,
panini e schiacciatine di ogni tipo!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Una volta mangiato qualcosa, ci trasferiamo tutti in un&amp;rsquo;altra zona del
C-base, ovvero quella somigliante ad una stazione spaziale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Il C-base infatti, secondo una leggenda metropolitana, sarebbe costruito
soprai resti di un&amp;rsquo;antica stazione spaziale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entrando nel cuore del C-base in effetti sembra di entrare proprio
all&amp;rsquo;interno di una &lt;strong&gt;stazione spaziale&lt;/strong&gt;. Le poltrone sono fatte come le
sedie di uno shuttle, al muro ci sono incastonati pezzi di schede madre,
processori ed altri componenti hardware. La &amp;ldquo;stazione&amp;rdquo; ospita anche un
bar dove viene venduta dell&amp;rsquo;ottima birra freschissima a soli 2€ a
bottiglia!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Il pomeriggio del summit prosegue con ben tre sessioni parallele di talk
e a fine serata viene organizzata una festa all&amp;rsquo;interno del C-base.
Questa volta la &lt;strong&gt;birra&lt;/strong&gt; viene offerta gratuitamente! Ci sistemiamo
tutti intorno ai tavoli, ognuno con il proprio tablet a parlare fra noi,
chattare, leggere email e qualcuno a bloggare in tempo reale quello che
succede intorno. Durante la serata ho avuto modo di conoscere meglio
&lt;strong&gt;Alberto Garcia&lt;/strong&gt;, uno sviluppatore spagnolo con il quale collaboro per
il progetto Vagalume (un player Last.fm di cui curo la traduzione in
italiano). Ho molto apprezzato inoltre che &lt;strong&gt;Quim Gil&lt;/strong&gt; (marketing
manager di Nokia per il progetto Maemo) sia venuto da ognuno di noi a
chiederci le nostre impressioni, le nostre idee e tutto quello che
potevamo dirgli sulla prima giornata del summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dopo essere stati alla festa fino a circa mezzanotte, faccio rientro in
albergo, visto che la mattina dopo ci sarebbe stata un&amp;rsquo;altra giornata
intensa di conferenze e talk tecnici.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Maemo Summit (Berlino) - giorno 1</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/maemo-summit-berlino-giorno-1/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/maemo-summit-berlino-giorno-1/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Come da programma, sono arrivato a &lt;strong&gt;Berlino&lt;/strong&gt; alle &lt;strong&gt;16:30&lt;/strong&gt; circa e
dopo aver raggiunto l&amp;rsquo;Hotel dove alloggio, ho cercato per prima cosa una
connessione wireless da poter utilizzare in camera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;L&amp;rsquo;Hotel dove mi trovo mette a disposizione una wireless a pagamento,
alla &amp;ldquo;modica&amp;rdquo; cifra di &lt;strong&gt;9 euro&lt;/strong&gt; al giorno! Controllando bene ho visto
che era disponibile anche un access point della
&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.t-mobile.net&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;T-Mobile&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (sempre a pagamento) che offriva
una connessione senza limiti per &lt;strong&gt;30 giorni a 29€&lt;/strong&gt;. Pur dovendo
rimanere soltanto 5 giorni ho optato per questa soluzione. Una piccola
nota per chi si trovasse a volerla utilizzare: la velocità di upload è
quella di una normale ADSL, ed il tempo di ping è attorno agli 80ms, la
&lt;strong&gt;velocità di download però è bassissima&lt;/strong&gt;, con &lt;strong&gt;solo 300 kbps&lt;/strong&gt;,
sufficienti appena per utilizzare Skype e navigare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Una volta connesso mi sono messo in contatto con i miei colleghi del
summit, in particolare con i due italiani che alloggiano nel mio stesso
hotel. Dopo essermi ambientato, mi sono subito aggiornato sulle novità
che riguardano Maemo, che erano state annunciate in questi giorni
all&amp;rsquo;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.osimworld.com/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Osim&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;un nuovo device che verrà fornito con un processore piu&amp;rsquo; potente di
quello attuale, ovvero un &lt;strong&gt;OMAP3&lt;/strong&gt;```&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;supporto &lt;strong&gt;HSPA&lt;/strong&gt; di serie&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;una &lt;strong&gt;videocamera&lt;/strong&gt; di qualità migliore&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;piu&amp;rsquo; spazio di archiviazione sul dispositivo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;rilascio di &lt;strong&gt;Maemo 5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quello che ancora non è stato detto è se &lt;strong&gt;Maemo 5&lt;/strong&gt; sara&amp;rsquo; compatibile
con gli attuali dispositivi N800/N810: Maemo 5 avra&amp;rsquo; il supporto per
&lt;strong&gt;OpenGL&lt;/strong&gt; che attualmente i dispositivi non hanno. Si pensa quindi che
possa essere rilasciata una particolare versione del sistema, senza
effetti grafici OpenGL, proprio per mantenere la compatibilità con
questi dispositivi. In caso contrario gli utenti saranno costretti ad
acquistare un nuovo dispositivo per poter godere delle nuove feature di
Maemo 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All&amp;rsquo;ora di cena ho avuto modo finalmente di conoscere &lt;strong&gt;Daniele Maio&lt;/strong&gt;,
uno degli italiani presenti al summit. Devo dire che Berlino (e
sopratutto la zona di Alexander Platz) ci ha abbastanza disorientati!
Non è stato così facile come credevamo trovare un posto tipico dove
poter cenare. Per la strada si incontravano diversi McDonald, Burger
King, Doner Kebab ecc&amp;hellip; ma pochissimi pub tipici.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finalmente la nostra fatica è stata ampiamente ripagata e ci siamo
sistemati in una birreria dove abbiamo ordinato, oltre a due birre
grandi, un ottimo &lt;strong&gt;stinco di maiale&lt;/strong&gt; con crauti, patate, cetriolo e
senape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finita la cena siamo subito rientrati, visto che la mattina dopo alle
&lt;strong&gt;ore 9:00&lt;/strong&gt; si sarebbero aperte le porte del
&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.c-base.org/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;C-base&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; per le conferenze in programma.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Maemo Summit sto arrivando!</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/maemo-summit-sto-arrivando/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/maemo-summit-sto-arrivando/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/maemo-summit-sto-arrivando/c-logo_claim_blue.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;493&#34;
	height=&#34;183&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;c-base&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;269&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;646px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grazie a &lt;strong&gt;Nokia&lt;/strong&gt;, avrò l&amp;rsquo;occasione fra pochi giorni di partecipare al
&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://wiki.maemo.org/Maemo_Summit_2008&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maemo Summit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; che si terrà
a &lt;strong&gt;Berlino&lt;/strong&gt;. Si svolgerà nei giorni di &lt;strong&gt;venerdi 19&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;sabato 20
settembre&lt;/strong&gt; e sarà ospitato nella splendida sede del
&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/C-base&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;C-base&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Il Maemo Summit è un meeting degli sviluppatori e appassionati di Maemo,
la piattaforma utilizzata sugli internet tablet della Nokia. Sarà
un&amp;rsquo;occasione per conoscere di persona tantissima gente con la quale fino
ad ora ho avuto a che fare soltanto tramite la mailing list o il canale
IRC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nei prossimi giorni sperò di riuscire a postare, quasi in tempo reale e
connessione internet permettendo, un report dettagliato di quello che
verrà fatto all&amp;rsquo;interno del C-base. Non mancheranno ovviamente le
fotografie, che avrò cura di pubblicare su Flickr!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
