<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Review on Andrea Grandi</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/categories/review/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Review on Andrea Grandi</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.andreagrandi.it/categories/review/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Simple and free solution to read content from RSS feeds on iOS and MacOS</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/simple-solution-to-read-rss-content-on-ios-macos/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/simple-solution-to-read-rss-content-on-ios-macos/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/simple-solution-to-read-rss-content-on-ios-macos/rss-sync-cover.webp" alt="Featured image of post Simple and free solution to read content from RSS feeds on iOS and MacOS" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reading news and blog posts can be quite time consuming if we manually go to news websites to check if something new is out or if we spend all day checking social media, waiting for people we follow to post their latest article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An efficient way to fetch new content is to follow the news sites and the blogs we want, using their &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt; feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the best way to do this for iOS and MacOS? &lt;strong&gt;There is no &amp;ldquo;best&amp;rdquo; way&lt;/strong&gt;, since there are plenty of RSS clients and combinations of services, but I will tell you a simple and free solution I&amp;rsquo;m using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;netnewswire-and-icloud-sync&#34;&gt;NetNewsWire and iCloud sync&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/simple-solution-to-read-rss-content-on-ios-macos/netnewsfeed-main.png&#34;
	width=&#34;2360&#34;
	height=&#34;1640&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;143&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;345px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The client I&amp;rsquo;m using is &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://netnewswire.com/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;NetNewsWire&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;open source&lt;/strong&gt; and available for both &lt;strong&gt;iOS&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;MacOS&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This client supports different synchronisation services, including &lt;strong&gt;iCloud&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;FeedBin&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Inoreader&lt;/strong&gt; or it can be used just on a single device, without using any of these services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I initially tried using Inoreader and it was &amp;ldquo;ok&amp;rdquo;, but it&amp;rsquo;s a paid service which injects ads in its free plan. Also, its cheaper paid plan only removes ads, without offering any additional value. I really couldn&amp;rsquo;t justify paying a subscription just to keep my feeds synced across devices, so &lt;strong&gt;I opted to use iCloud&lt;/strong&gt; which, in my case, is exactly what I need and I don&amp;rsquo;t have to purchase any additional plan (I&amp;rsquo;m already on a paid plan, but even the free plan is enough for this).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure there are better solutions around (especially RSS clients) and I would be glad to hear about them, but for now this simple client and iCloud is all I need to enjoy the news and read blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>iA Writer Authorship: a brilliant feature with a problematic implementation</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/ia-writer-authorship-brilliant-feature-problematic-implementation/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/ia-writer-authorship-brilliant-feature-problematic-implementation/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/ia-writer-authorship-brilliant-feature-problematic-implementation/ia-writer-authorship-cover.webp" alt="Featured image of post iA Writer Authorship: a brilliant feature with a problematic implementation" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I recently started using &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://ia.net/writer&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;iA Writer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to edit my MarkDown files on iPad and I&amp;rsquo;m honestly quite impressed by its simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the latest version they introduced a feature called &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://ia.net/writer/support/editor/authorship&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Authorship&lt;/a&gt; which basically helps you to keep track of external contributors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, suppose you asked a friend (or even ChatGPT) to write a conclusion for one of your articles, you copy-paste the text on your article and you start editing it. How do you keep track of what you or the other source wrote? With the Authorship feature, text edited by you will be rendered in a different way, so you can distinguish it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is a brilliant idea and even if I don&amp;rsquo;t make much usage of GPT to write my posts (almost none so far), I may use it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with this feature is that if you enable it for one of your documents, iA Writer will add an &amp;ldquo;hidden&amp;rdquo; &lt;code&gt;Authorship&lt;/code&gt; section at the end of the file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section won&amp;rsquo;t be visible in iA while editing the text, but it will be visible in any other editor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, I plan to use iA Writer to write my blog posts, which I then push to GitHub using &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://workingcopy.app/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Working Copy&lt;/a&gt;, where they are finally transformed by Hugo to my static website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unless I edit the file with a different editor&lt;/strong&gt;, if I submit my article as is, &lt;strong&gt;Hugo&lt;/strong&gt; (but even Pelican, or Jekyll etc&amp;hellip; basically any engine which doesn&amp;rsquo;t know how to handle this block of information) &lt;strong&gt;will render the Authorship block into the final HTML page&lt;/strong&gt;, which is something nobody really wants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;possible-solutions&#34;&gt;Possible solutions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked iA people on Mastodon about this issue and &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://mastodon.online/@ia/112037948788436778&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;they told me&lt;/a&gt; they had considered different options but in any case something will break for someone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree, it&amp;rsquo;s not easy to find a solution which can cover every possible case, but I still think there could be margin for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;saving-authorship-in-an-external-file&#34;&gt;Saving Authorship in an external file&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If these additional data was saved in an external file, it would be much easier to exclude it from the built pages. By the way, this would mean spreading the information across different files, making it more difficult to maintain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;using-yaml-metadata&#34;&gt;Using YAML metadata&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding the Authorship as metadata could be the best option, for a couple of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;iA Writer already makes use of YAML metadata where you can add information, so existing users would be used to see something at the beginning of the file which is not their content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any unknown metadata is usually ignored by static websites generators (at least Hugo and Pelican behave in this way) so the Authorship won&amp;rsquo;t be rendered in the final HTML page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-workaround-for-hugo&#34;&gt;A workaround for Hugo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I hope iA will consider giving alternative options in the future, I&amp;rsquo;ve written a simple script you can use to remove all Authorship blocks from any MarkDown file found in your content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/andreagrandi/800e5e33ec05f8d51f61a1cdc4fc4d91.js?file=strip-annotation.sh&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that this will remove any Authorship block from your MarkDown files, even if you include them in a code block. If you want to improve the script, feel free to do it and let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction of the Authorship feature in iA Writer presents a creative solution for managing and distinguishing between original content and external contributions within documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the feature offers significant advantages for content creators seeking to track their collaborations, it also introduces challenges, particularly in the integration with static site generators like Hugo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My advice is that, as users, we give some &lt;strong&gt;constructive feedback&lt;/strong&gt; to iA (you can contact them at &lt;code&gt;support+newfeature@ia.net&lt;/code&gt;) to let them know how to improve this feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, if you are more familiar with GitHub, you can discuss this specific feature directly in their &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/iainc/Markdown-Annotations&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Self hosting a Copilot replacement: my personal experience</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/self-hosting-copilot-replacement/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/self-hosting-copilot-replacement/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/self-hosting-copilot-replacement/self-hosting-copilot-cover.webp" alt="Featured image of post Self hosting a Copilot replacement: my personal experience" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;For my job (Software Developer) I make a daily use of tools like &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/features/copilot&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;GitHub Copilot&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://chat.openai.com/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;ChatGPT&lt;/a&gt;. I want to explore alternative solutions which can be hosted autonomusly, without relying on an external service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I continue, let me clarify that these are &lt;strong&gt;tools&lt;/strong&gt; which makes my job faster, they don&amp;rsquo;t do the job for me: a wrong assumption made by so many people is that AI tools will do the work for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is quite &lt;strong&gt;not true&lt;/strong&gt;. You are still responsible of knowing what to do, understanding the problem, asking the right questions and knowing what to do with the answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you regularly search for stuff on Google or any other engine, to find examples in blog posts or Stack Overflow, read someone else example and then adapt the code for your needs, there is nothing wrong automating this: &lt;strong&gt;you are still in charge of the final result&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-experiment&#34;&gt;The experiment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I recently experimented with &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/ollama-running-llm-locally/&#34; &gt;local LLMs using Ollama&lt;/a&gt;, I wanted to figure out if I could use some of these models to &lt;strong&gt;replace GitHub Copilot&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My intent is not to save some money (my company pays for these tools) or for privacy reasons (it would be pointless to keep your code &amp;ldquo;secret&amp;rdquo; from GitHub if you use it to host it), but to &lt;strong&gt;find out how good these alternative tools are&lt;/strong&gt; and&amp;hellip; for fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;setup-and-available-resources&#34;&gt;Setup and available resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The laptop I&amp;rsquo;m using is a MacBook Pro with &lt;strong&gt;M2 Pro&lt;/strong&gt; CPU and &lt;strong&gt;32 GB RAM&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This machine must be able to run my basic &lt;strong&gt;requirements&lt;/strong&gt;, which are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Docker (running my work containers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VSCode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Safari / Chrome&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s see if it can also run a Copilot replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tested-models-and-extensions&#34;&gt;Tested models and extensions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, to run a Copilot replacement, you need to be able to run an LLM and use one of the available extensions for VSCode (in my case I use VSCode, but similar extensions exist for other IDEs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m running the models locally using &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://ollama.com&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Ollama&lt;/a&gt;. If you need to know how to use it, you can refer to my &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/ollama-running-llm-locally/&#34; &gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;models&lt;/strong&gt; I tested are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;stable-code:3b-code-q4_0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;codellama:7b-code-q4_K_M&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;codellama:13b-code-q4_K_M&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number before the &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; usually represents the number of parameters (&lt;strong&gt;3 billions&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;7 billions&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;13 billions&lt;/strong&gt; etc&amp;hellip;) and you approximately need &lt;strong&gt;4 GB&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;8 GB&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;16 GB RAM&lt;/strong&gt; to use them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://about.meta.com&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Meta&lt;/a&gt; has released models with &lt;strong&gt;34 billions&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;70 billions&lt;/strong&gt; parameters, which are even more powerful, and you can find them here: &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://ollama.com/library/codellama&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;https://ollama.com/library/codellama&lt;/a&gt; but you will need &lt;strong&gt;64-128 GB RAM&lt;/strong&gt; to run them properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extensions I tested are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LLama Coder&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=ex3ndr.llama-coder&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=ex3ndr.llama-coder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code GPT&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=DanielSanMedium.dscodegpt&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=DanielSanMedium.dscodegpt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;twinny&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=rjmacarthy.twinny&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=rjmacarthy.twinny&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results I got have been quite mixed and &lt;strong&gt;mostly depending on the LLM model&lt;/strong&gt; I was testing, rather than on the extension I was using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A model like &lt;code&gt;stable-code:3b-code-q4_0&lt;/code&gt; was quite &lt;strong&gt;fast&lt;/strong&gt; to complete the code I was typing, &lt;strong&gt;but very often&lt;/strong&gt; giving me &lt;strong&gt;wrong&lt;/strong&gt; code or pure garbage (ie: the model wasn&amp;rsquo;t even able to correctly structure a simple Python method or to maintain the correct indentation)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Models like &lt;code&gt;codellama:7b-code-q4_K_M&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;codellama:13b-code-q4_K_M&lt;/code&gt; were giving me &lt;strong&gt;better results&lt;/strong&gt; but despite having 32 GB RAM available and a quite fast CPU, they were &lt;strong&gt;taking 3-4 seconds&lt;/strong&gt; to complete what I was typing, making themselves useless (at least for my use case).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;None of them was even remotely close to the speed and accuracy of GitHub Copilot&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the idea of having a personal and private instance of a code assistant is interesting (and can also be the only available option in certain environments), &lt;strong&gt;the reality is that achieving the same level of performance as GitHub Copilot is quite challenging&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these challenges, I think with time both available models and extensions &lt;strong&gt;will get better&lt;/strong&gt; and better, improving their quality and maybe reducing the amount of required resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case I missed some better model or extension, please feel free to &lt;strong&gt;let me know&lt;/strong&gt; in the comments. I will be glad to do more tests and update this posts or write a new one in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the mean time&lt;/strong&gt;, at least for my personale usage, I think I will &lt;strong&gt;stick with GitHub Copilot&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>ebook: valgono la pena rispetto ai libri cartacei? L&#39;esempio Amazon Kindle</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/ebook-valgono-la-pena-rispetto-ai-libri-cartacei-lesempio-amazon-kindle/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/ebook-valgono-la-pena-rispetto-ai-libri-cartacei-lesempio-amazon-kindle/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;kindle-300x211.jpg&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/ebook-valgono-la-pena-rispetto-ai-libri-cartacei-lesempio-amazon-kindle/kindle-300x211.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;300&#34;
	height=&#34;211&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;kindle&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;142&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;341px&#34;
	
&gt;{ width=60% }&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In questo periodo diversi conoscenti mi stanno facendo domande su come
siano gli ebook e se valga la pena farne uso rispetto ai normali libri
cartacei. Recentemente ho avuto modo di acquistare il lettore
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.amazon.it/Kindle-dispositivo-wireless-inchiostro-elettronico/dp/B0051QVF7A/ref=amb_link_162561647_2?pf_rd_m=A11IL2PNWYJU7H&amp;amp;pf_rd_s=center-1&amp;amp;pf_rd_r=0DNDRW6Q67KH6PZGYECK&amp;amp;pf_rd_t=101&amp;amp;pf_rd_p=270371827&amp;amp;pf_rd_i=426865031&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Kindle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
di &lt;strong&gt;Amazon&lt;/strong&gt; e devo ammettere di essere rimasto molto soddisfatto. Ho
cercato di raccogliere le principali domande che mi sono state fatte al
riguardo, sperando di fornire una panoramica completa sui libri in
formato elettronico e sui relativi lettori.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non è scomodo leggere sul Kindke?&lt;/strong&gt; Assolutamente no. Non dovete
immaginare il Kindle come un tablet (anzi, chi cerca un qualcosa che
funzioni anche come tablet ha proprio sbagliato prodotto. Kindle è fatto
per leggere libri.), lo schermo infatti non è un normale LCD come quelli
dei tablet o dei portatili, ma una speciale superficie dove le parole
vengono disegnate tramite l&amp;rsquo;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/E-ink&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;e-ink&lt;/a&gt;.
Lo schermo del Kindle non è retroilluminato e per leggere, così come per
un libro normale, c&amp;rsquo;è bisogno o della luce del sole o di stare vicino ad
una lampada. Gli occhi quindi non si stancano ed è possibile andare
avanti a leggere per ore, senza notare differenze rispetto alla lettura
di un libro normale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quanto costano i libri in formato elettronico?&lt;/strong&gt; Di solito il costo è
di &lt;strong&gt;3-4€ in meno&lt;/strong&gt; rispetto alla versione cartacea. Potrebbero costare
molto meno se la legge italiana (ancora una volta cieca di fronte alle
innovazioni) non equiparasse gli ebook a dei prodotti elettronici. L&amp;rsquo;IVA
sugli ebook è infatti del 21% e non viene assolta come per i libri
cartacei. Va detto anche che moltissimi libri, per i quali sono ormai
scaduti i diritti di autore, sono disponibili gratuitamente. Volete
leggere &lt;em&gt;La Divina Commedia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pirandello&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;I Promessi Sposi&lt;/em&gt; ecc&amp;hellip;?!
Benissimo. Questi e molti altri libri sono scaricabili gratuitamente.
Kindle al momento offre &amp;ldquo;soltanto&amp;rdquo; &lt;strong&gt;16.000 titoli&lt;/strong&gt; in italiano, ma è
ovviamente possibile accedere anche a tutti gli altri titoli disponibili
in lingua straniera, per un totale di &lt;strong&gt;quasi un milione di libri a
disposizione&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quali sono i vantaggi per chi scrive?&lt;/strong&gt; Gli scrittori, grazie agli
ebook, hanno un modo ancora piu&amp;rsquo; facile e redditizio per pubblicare i
propri libri. Attualmente, se uno scrittore vuole pubblicare un libro,
deve trovare un editore che lo reputi interessante e decida di investire
per pubblicarlo. Visto che l&amp;rsquo;editore di assume un rischio molto alto, la
maggior parte del compenso va a lui. Con Amazon invece è possibile
pubblicare un proprio libro in modo economico e veloce. Non c&amp;rsquo;è
necessità di stampare migliaia di copie di un libro, così come avviene
per il cartaceo. I compensi inoltre sono molto alti: il &lt;strong&gt;70% del
ricavato va a chi scrive il libro&lt;/strong&gt;, non all&amp;rsquo;editore. Su un libro da 10€
quindi, all&amp;rsquo;autore rimangono 7€.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Riassumiamo i vantaggi degli ebook&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;economici (costano 3-4€ in meno, molti sono persino gratuiti)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ecologici (non c&amp;rsquo;è bisogno di stampare migliaia di copie)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maggiori introiti per chi scrive i libri&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;un e-reader è leggero, può contenere oltre 1000 libri, ottima autonomia con batterie che durano 1 mese&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;comodità di poter acquistare un libro direttamente da casa ed averlo in pochi minuti&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nessun pericolo di acquistare un libro che non ci piace: con Kindle è possibile avere una copia dei primi capitoli del libro, senza spendere niente, in modo da valutare se il libro valga veramente la pena di essere letto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Se posso aggiungere un vantaggio, del tutto soggettivo, ma che
personalmente è il piu&amp;rsquo; importante: gli ebook mi hanno fatto tornare
anche la voglia di leggere!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
