<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Privacy on Andrea Grandi</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/tags/privacy/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Privacy on Andrea Grandi</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.andreagrandi.it/tags/privacy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Kagi: a paid search engine which is worth the money</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/kagi-paid-search-engine/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/kagi-paid-search-engine/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/kagi-paid-search-engine/kagi-landing-page.jpeg" alt="Featured image of post Kagi: a paid search engine which is worth the money" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s a not a &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://mashable.com/article/google-search-low-quality-research&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;news&lt;/a&gt; anymore that Google, the search engine which once was the best available, doesn’t work anymore for a lot of users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its results are full of ads, they are not &lt;strong&gt;optimised&lt;/strong&gt; for &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.searchenginejournal.com/biased-google-search-results-are-hurting-users-harvard-study-claims/135824/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;users&lt;/a&gt;, nor for &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://simpleblog.ai/blog/google-ads-can-do-more-for-customers/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;advertisers&lt;/a&gt; and sometimes they also include &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.helpnetsecurity.com/2023/01/18/google-ads-increasingly-pointing-to-malware/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;malware&lt;/a&gt;. Their main goal is &lt;strong&gt;to boost ad revenue&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why it’s still the most used search engine in the world? Well that’s “easy”, because Google &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.theverge.com/2023/10/26/23933206/google-apple-search-deal-safari-18-billion&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;pays&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (a lot!) &lt;strong&gt;to be the default search engine&lt;/strong&gt; everywhere and users are often lazy to change their habits or don’t know alternatives are available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;kagi&#34;&gt;Kagi&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/kagi-paid-search-engine/kagi-landing-page.jpeg&#34;
	width=&#34;2360&#34;
	height=&#34;1420&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;Kagi landing page&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;166&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;398px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-impressions&#34;&gt;My impressions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After hearing a lot of good things about this search engine (especially from the folks on Mastodon), I decided to give it a try (there is a &lt;strong&gt;trial plan available&lt;/strong&gt; with 100 search queries included, so don’t take my word and please test yourself!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first impression was terrific. I was finally able to find what I was looking for with the second or third (and sometimes with first) link in the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Google I usually had to scroll past a few &lt;strong&gt;ads&lt;/strong&gt;, then ignore &lt;strong&gt;old web pages&lt;/strong&gt; (but with a good SEO), then go past another couple of &lt;strong&gt;irrelevant links&lt;/strong&gt; and finally find what I was looking for. But the point is that you never know how bad the results are until you click, read a few lines and take a decision. At that point you already have &lt;strong&gt;wasted a lot of time just&lt;/strong&gt; to find the right thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Kagi I just save a lot of time, get better results and nobody is tracking what I search for to serve me related ads at later time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The customisation &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://blog.kagi.com/kagi-features&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;features&lt;/a&gt; make the results I get even better and more tailored to my needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-choosing-kagi&#34;&gt;Why choosing Kagi&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Privacy:&lt;/strong&gt; there are &lt;strong&gt;no ads&lt;/strong&gt; in the results and there is &lt;strong&gt;no tracking&lt;/strong&gt; in place. What you search is private. While Kagi relies on some existing search engines (Google, Bing, Brave etc…) they use them as a source of data and all the queries are always anonymised before being sent to them. Once their requests are back, results are aggregated and customised for the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User custom results:&lt;/strong&gt; users can decide to exclude certain websites from ever appearing in their results, or rank higher or lower certain other websites. Tired of always seeing that click-bait website appearing? You can block it! Do you prefer to first look stuff in Wikipedia if available? You can rank it higher etc…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lenses:&lt;/strong&gt; once you get your results back, you can decide to filter them further by using lenses. For example you can use the “&lt;em&gt;Recipe&lt;/em&gt;” lens, to search specifically for recipes, or the “&lt;em&gt;Discussions&lt;/em&gt;” one to search inside discussion forums.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instant answers:&lt;/strong&gt; sometimes you can get an instant answer when you search for something, which already includes a lot of information, without the need to click on the found link. For example, searching for &lt;code&gt;Python for loop&lt;/code&gt; will give you this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/kagi-paid-search-engine/python-for-loop.jpeg&#34;
	width=&#34;1640&#34;
	height=&#34;846&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;Python for loop&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;193&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;465px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summariser:&lt;/strong&gt; this feature is still experimental, but I think it’s one of the best features available (AI haters please look somewhere else!). &lt;strong&gt;Kagi Summariser&lt;/strong&gt; is able to create a summary of almost any public resource you can provide: a link to a web page, a podcast, a YouTube video etc… it uses AI to transcribe audio/video and then it creates a summary of it. It saves me a lot of time, depending on what I’m looking for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-kagi-with-safari&#34;&gt;Using Kagi with Safari&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use Safari as my main browser and unfortunately this browser doesn’t let you add any custom search engine, so Kagi engineers had to use a quick hack. They released a &lt;strong&gt;Safari extension&lt;/strong&gt; which intercepts any query sent to your default engine and redirects it to Kagi. My personal advice? Change your default engine to &lt;strong&gt;DuckDuckGo&lt;/strong&gt; or something else you trust if you don’t want to leak stuff to Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pricing&#34;&gt;Pricing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kagi doesn’t offer a free plan (it only has a &lt;strong&gt;trial with 100 queries&lt;/strong&gt; included) and it has three paid plans:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Starter:&lt;/strong&gt; it costs 5$/month and includes 300 queries/month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Professional:&lt;/strong&gt; it costs 10$/month, has unlimited queries and includes AI tools like Kagi Summariser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ultimate:&lt;/strong&gt; it costs 25$/month, it’s like Professional plan but you get preview access to features which are still in development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally have the &lt;strong&gt;Professional&lt;/strong&gt; plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope I stimulated your curiosity to at least convince you to use the trial. I’m curious to hear your opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Contact Tracing: non e&#39; solo un problema di privacy o di sicurezza</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/contact-tracing-non-solo-un-problema-di-privacy/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/contact-tracing-non-solo-un-problema-di-privacy/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;contact-tracing-in-italia&#34;&gt;Contact Tracing in Italia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Negli ultimi giorni non si fa che parlare di &lt;strong&gt;Immuni&lt;/strong&gt;, la app che il Governo Italiano avrebbe scelto, come soluzione di &lt;strong&gt;contact tracing&lt;/strong&gt; per il &lt;strong&gt;COVID-19&lt;/strong&gt;, e vengono sollevati molti dubbi (si va da quelli legittimi a quelli che rasentano il complottismo) al riguardo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Per &amp;ldquo;contact tracing&amp;rdquo; si intende una soluzione che, mediante l&amp;rsquo;uso della tecnologia, ci permetta di creare una traccia di tutti i nostri contatti e fare in modo che quando uno di essi dichiarera&amp;rsquo; di essere positivo al COVID-19, le persone che sono entrate in contatto con lui/lei ricevano una notifica.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prima che proseguiate nella lettura, mi sento in dovere di fare &lt;strong&gt;una doverosa premessa&lt;/strong&gt;: da oltre 20 anni mi occupo di sviluppo software ed ho esperienza di utilizzo di svariate tecnologie anche in ambiti in cui di solito e&amp;rsquo; l&amp;rsquo;uomo a prendere una decisione. La cosa piu&amp;rsquo; importante pero&amp;rsquo; e&amp;rsquo; che &lt;strong&gt;non sono ne&amp;rsquo; un virologo, ne&amp;rsquo; un epidemiologo, ne&amp;rsquo; un medico&lt;/strong&gt;. Mi limitero&amp;rsquo; quindi ad un&amp;rsquo;analisi dei fatti, rimanendo nell&amp;rsquo;ambito delle mie competenze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La mia personale opinione (tuttavia irrilevante) e&amp;rsquo; che una soluzione tecnologica possa essere di aiuto nelle prossime fasi della pandemia, ma dovra&amp;rsquo; essere accompagnata da un&amp;rsquo;accurata verifica manuale dei risultati.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-dubbi-al-momento&#34;&gt;I dubbi al momento&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I maggiori dubbi al momento riguardando &lt;strong&gt;l&amp;rsquo;efficacia&lt;/strong&gt; della soluzione scelta, la &lt;strong&gt;sicurezza&lt;/strong&gt; dei dati sensibili che verranno raccolti e quelli sulla &lt;strong&gt;privacy&lt;/strong&gt; delle persone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ritengo tutti questi punti molto importanti, ma sono dell&amp;rsquo;idea che prima di tutto questo si debba fare un punto sulla &lt;strong&gt;trasparenza&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;il-governo-e-la-task-force&#34;&gt;Il Governo e la task force&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alcune settimane fa il Governo ha annunciato la creazione di una &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://innovazione.gov.it/DM-task-force/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;task force di tecnici&lt;/a&gt;, che avrebbe dovuto produrre un report con suggerimenti e linee guida, in modo che il governo potesse effettuare una scelta ragionata. Molti di questi nomi sono noti a chi e&amp;rsquo; del settore (ne conosco personalmente alcuni) e ritengo personalmente che fosse un ottimo punto di partenza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Il problema pero&amp;rsquo; e&amp;rsquo; che &lt;strong&gt;l&amp;rsquo;intera task force e&amp;rsquo; stata messa sotto Non Disclosure Agreement&lt;/strong&gt;, che tradotto in termini semplici significa che a nessuno di loro e&amp;rsquo; permesso di rilasciare commenti o dichiarazioni in pubblico, ne&amp;rsquo; di rivelare alcuna informazione su quanto prodotto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;il-report-della-task-force&#34;&gt;Il report della task force&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Il &lt;strong&gt;report&lt;/strong&gt;, ad oggi, &lt;strong&gt;non e&amp;rsquo; stato reso pubblico&lt;/strong&gt;: in che modo possiamo valutare i criteri utilizzati per scegliere la soluzione, se non ci e&amp;rsquo; permesso di leggere il report?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come facciamo a verificare &lt;strong&gt;che il Governo abbia effettivamente seguito le indicazioni&lt;/strong&gt; dei tecnici o se abbia preferito fare di testa propria?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;la-soluzione-scelta-quali-criteri&#34;&gt;La soluzione scelta: quali criteri?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Al momento non esiste un &amp;ldquo;white paper&amp;rdquo; che ci descriva la soluzione proposta e adottata. In base a &lt;strong&gt;quali criteri&lt;/strong&gt; e&amp;rsquo; stata scelta proprio questa soluzione?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;quali-conseguenze-dopo-una-notifica&#34;&gt;Quali conseguenze dopo una notifica?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supponiamo di ricevere una notifica che ci avvisa che il giorno X siamo stati per un certo periodo di tempo vicini ad un&amp;rsquo;altra persona che si e&amp;rsquo; poi dichiarata positiva. Quale sara&amp;rsquo; la diretta conseguenza?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A) Qualcuno verra&amp;rsquo; a farci un tampone di verifica il prima possibile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;B) Ci verra&amp;rsquo; imposto un periodo di quarantena senza alcuna verifica&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C) Potremo ignorare la notifica&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Se le conseguenze di questa importante notifica non vengono stabilite a priori, molti non vorranno rischiare di essere costretti in casa, magari per un falso negativo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nota&lt;/strong&gt;: le possibilita&amp;rsquo; di un falso positivo sono davvero molte. Basandosi sul raggio di azione del Bluetooth, in teoria potremmo essere a 1 metro di distanza da una persona infetta, ma essere nella stanza accanto (e quindi in totale sicurezza). Oppure potremmo passare accanto ad una persona infetta mentre siamo in macchina con il finestrino chiuso. Per non parlare poi degli operatori sanitari: in alcuni casi, loro hanno la certezza di trovarsi nei paraggi di persone infette. Verrebbero considerati infetti anche loro? E quando la sera tornano a casa dai loro coniugi e familiari, sarebbero anche essi considerati positivi dalla app?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;closed-source&#34;&gt;Closed Source&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonostante le raccomandazioni della commissione Europea, pare che il codice sorgente della app non sara&amp;rsquo; pubblico (ma verra&amp;rsquo; rilasciato solo al Governo Italiano). Questo significa che non sara&amp;rsquo; possibile un controllo da parte di terze parti, e non ci sara&amp;rsquo; alcuna garanzia su quello che la app possa fare con i nostri dati (ne&amp;rsquo; sara&amp;rsquo; facile scovare e segnalare bug di sicurezza).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aggiornamento (21/04/2020): il governo ha annunciato in &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://innovazione.gov.it/un-aggiornamento-sull-applicazione-di-contact-tracing-digitale-per-l-emergenza-coronavirus/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;un aggiornamento&lt;/a&gt;, che la app verra&amp;rsquo; rilasciata sotto licenza &lt;strong&gt;Open Source (MPL 2.0)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusioni&#34;&gt;Conclusioni&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Qualsiasi strada si decida di prendere, e&amp;rsquo; fondamentale che il processo decisionale che ha portato a tale scelta sia quanto piu&amp;rsquo; &lt;strong&gt;trasparente&lt;/strong&gt; possibile. Solo in questo modo si potra&amp;rsquo; ottenere la fiducia del maggior numero di persone e cercare di raggiungere l&amp;rsquo;effetto desiderato. Per il momento, tutta questa trasparenza non c&amp;rsquo;e&amp;rsquo; stata.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Google is moving some EU citizens data to US</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/google-is-moving-eu-citizens-data-to-us/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/google-is-moving-eu-citizens-data-to-us/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-going-on&#34;&gt;What is going on&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may have heard already, because of &lt;strong&gt;brexit&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/gadgets-and-tech/news/google-uk-us-data-brexit-gdpr-trump-protection-information-a9348191.html&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Google is moving UK citizens data&lt;/a&gt; from the Northern Ireland data controller to the US one (Google LLC).
Leaving the EU, UK citizens are not protected anymore by GDPR, and while this may be unfair, Google is legally allowed to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if I&amp;rsquo;m an Italian citizen and I live in Italy, a few days ago I received this email from them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;google-data-controller-email.png&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/google-is-moving-eu-citizens-data-to-us/google-data-controller-email.png&#34;
	width=&#34;1122&#34;
	height=&#34;618&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;google data controller&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;181&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;435px&#34;
	
&gt;{ width=90% }&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;whats-wrong-with-it&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s wrong with it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is that I&amp;rsquo;m an &lt;strong&gt;Italian citizen&lt;/strong&gt;, living in &lt;strong&gt;Italy&lt;/strong&gt;.
I &lt;strong&gt;have nothing to do with UK&lt;/strong&gt; (even if I lived there for a few years in the past, my account was created from Italy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do they mention &amp;ldquo;UK leaving EU&amp;rdquo; to me, if I don&amp;rsquo;t live in UK?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried to contact them multiple times on their &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Google&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;@Google&lt;/a&gt; account on Twitter, but I got no reply at all. I tried to search online and it looks like I&amp;rsquo;m not alone, they are doing this to many other people: &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://support.google.com/accounts/thread/29317992?hl=en&amp;amp;authuser=1&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;https://support.google.com/accounts/thread/29317992?hl=en&amp;amp;authuser=1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;looking-for-help&#34;&gt;Looking for help&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What should I do? Is this legally allowed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there was an easy way to complain with them, I would have done it already, but I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to search on their website
(even googling it&amp;hellip; no pun intended) but &lt;strong&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find a single contact form&lt;/strong&gt; to report this issue and of course &lt;strong&gt;they are ignoring&lt;/strong&gt; both Twitter and that forum I linked previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should I &lt;strong&gt;report them&lt;/strong&gt; to the &lt;strong&gt;Privacy Authority&lt;/strong&gt;? If yes, how?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;full-text-of-the-email&#34;&gt;Full text of the email&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the full text of the email I received:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 3
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 4
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 5
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 6
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 7
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 8
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 9
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;10
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;11
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;12
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;13
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;14
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;15
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;16
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;17
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;18
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;19
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;20
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;21
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;22
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;23
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;24
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;25
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;26
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;27
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;28
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;29
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;30
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;31
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;32
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;33
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;34
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;35
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;36
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;37
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;We’re improving our Terms of Service and making them easier for you to understand. 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;The changes will take effect on 31 March 2020, and they won’t impact the way that you use 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;Google services. And, because the United Kingdom (UK) is leaving the European Union (EU), 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;Google LLC will now be the service provider and the data controller responsible for your 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;information and for complying with applicable privacy laws for UK consumer users.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;For more details, we’ve provided a summary of the key changes and Frequently asked questions. 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;And the next time that you visit Google, you’ll have the chance to review and accept the new Terms. 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;At a glance, here’s what this update means for you:
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;• 	Improved readability: While our Terms remain a legal document, we’ve done our best to make them 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    easier to understand, including by adding links to useful information and providing definitions.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;• 	Better communication: We’ve clearly explained when we’ll make changes to our services 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    (like adding or removing a feature) and when we’ll restrict or end a user’s access. 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    And we’ll do more to notify you when a change negatively impacts your experience on our services.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;• 	Adding Google Chrome, Google Chrome OS and Google Drive to the Terms: Our improved Terms now 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    cover Google Chrome, Google Chrome OS and Google Drive, which also have service-specific terms 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    and policies to help you understand what’s unique to those services.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;• 	Your service provider and data controller is now Google LLC: Because the UK is leaving the EU, 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    we’ve updated our Terms so that a United States-based company, Google LLC, is now your service 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    provider instead of Google Ireland Limited. Google LLC will also become the data controller 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    responsible for your information and complying with applicable privacy laws. 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    We’re making similar changes to the Terms of Service for YouTube, YouTube Paid Services and 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    Google Play. These changes to our Terms and privacy policy don’t affect your privacy settings 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    or the way that we treat your information (see the privacy policy for details). 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    As a reminder, you can always visit your Google Account to review your privacy settings and 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    manage how your data is used.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;If you’re the guardian of a child under the age required to manage their own Google Account and 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;you use Family Link to manage their use of Google services, please note that when you accept 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;our new Terms, you do so on their behalf as well, and you may want to discuss these changes with them.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;And of course, if you don’t agree to our new Terms and what we can expect from each other as you 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;use our services, you can find more information about your options in our Frequently asked questions.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;Thank you for using Google’s services.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;Your Google team
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Trusted Computing: perchè fidarsi di chi non si fida di noi?</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/trusted-computing-perche-fidarsi-di-chi-non-si-fida-di-noi/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/trusted-computing-perche-fidarsi-di-chi-non-si-fida-di-noi/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/trusted-computing-perche-fidarsi-di-chi-non-si-fida-di-noi/trusted.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;720&#34;
	height=&#34;576&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;trusted&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;125&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;300px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E&amp;rsquo; &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://punto-informatico.it/2442404/Telefonia/News/google-cancella-remoto-applicativi-android.aspx&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;notizia di questi giorni&lt;/a&gt;
il fatto che Google abbia previsto un meccanismo di &amp;ldquo;sicurezza&amp;rdquo; che
consentirà a loro stessi di &lt;strong&gt;rimuovere automaticamente&lt;/strong&gt;, dai
telefonini &lt;strong&gt;GPhone&lt;/strong&gt; che verranno venduti, le applicazioni non ritenute
sicure. Google avrà quindi la possibilità di controllare i propri
dispositivi da remoto, accedere alla memoria del telefono e rimuovere
quello che non desidera ci sia installato: chi ci assicura che non si
mettano a controllare pure il testo degli SMS che inviamo o riceviamo,
magari per inviarci pubblicità mirata a seconda delle nostre esigenze?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Della stessa pasta sono fatti anche i dispositivi della &lt;strong&gt;Apple&lt;/strong&gt;, in
particolare l&amp;rsquo;&lt;strong&gt;iPhone&lt;/strong&gt;. Anche questo dispositivo &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://punto-informatico.it/2346662/Telefonia/News/iphone-3g-libero-ma-non-troppo.aspx&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;incorpora infatti un chip&lt;/a&gt;
che impedisce alle applicazioni non consentite di girare sul telefonino.
L&amp;rsquo;unico modo per installare applicazioni sull&amp;rsquo;iPhone è quello di
scaricarle dall&amp;rsquo;&lt;strong&gt;Apple Store&lt;/strong&gt;, ed ovviamente Apple &lt;strong&gt;si riserva il
diritto di decidere&lt;/strong&gt; quali applicazioni possano apparire nello store e
quali invece no, ed una nota nella licenza che devono firmare gli
sviluppatori di applicazioni per iPhone, si dice anche che essi non
possono in alcun modo dire pubblicamente che una loro applicazione è
stata esclusa dallo store. Tutto questo in nome della nostra
&amp;ldquo;sicurezza&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
