<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Sprint on Andrea Grandi</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/tags/sprint/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Sprint on Andrea Grandi</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.andreagrandi.it/tags/sprint/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Ubuntu Release Sprint: calling for feedback!</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/ubuntu-release-sprint-calling-for-feedback/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/ubuntu-release-sprint-calling-for-feedback/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;During the last UDS party, I had an idea to improve Ubuntu development,
but I didn&amp;rsquo;t know if it could be a good idea or a stupid one, so I
talked to &lt;strong&gt;Daniel Holbach&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;David Planella&lt;/strong&gt; about it and they
were happy to hear about it and Daniel told me to talk about
this directly to &lt;strong&gt;Mark&lt;/strong&gt; (and I did it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s explain the basic idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From an UDS and the next one, it would be useful to have a
development sprint where people can talk about assigned UDS blueprints,
at which point they are on their tasks, if they have any problems and if
they will finish them within the next UDS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course Canonical cannot organize another meeting, it would be
very expensive, so the idea is: why don&amp;rsquo;t we use &lt;strong&gt;Google Hangout&lt;/strong&gt; to
organize the sprint? I has a limit of 10 people, I know, but we could
select (for example) 5 from the community and 5 from Canonical. There
would be parallel meeting and tracks, we would use the same blueprints
used during the last UDS and we would add further notes. The
attendees would be able to listen and watch the stream and make
questions through the available chat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve also created a &lt;strong&gt;wiki&lt;/strong&gt; page with more informations and you can
find it here: &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://wiki.ubuntu.com/UbuntuReleaseSprint&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;https://wiki.ubuntu.com/UbuntuReleaseSprint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think about? I know that Canonical is already
organizing sprints and this could be a way to involve more the Ubuntu
Community. Maybe we should schedule a session &lt;strong&gt;at next UDS&lt;/strong&gt; to talk
about this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to get some &lt;strong&gt;feedback&lt;/strong&gt; from you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
