<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Community on Andrea Grandi</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/tags/community/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Community on Andrea Grandi</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.andreagrandi.it/tags/community/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Building a healthy and sustainable funding model for open source software</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/building-healthy-sustainable-funding-model-opensource-software/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/building-healthy-sustainable-funding-model-opensource-software/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you work in software development, chances are high that your company is &lt;strong&gt;using open source software to build their products&lt;/strong&gt;. Nowadays open source software is nearly everywhere: it can be included in your operating system, in commercial software or it can be responsible for hosting your website or your application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will focus mainly on &lt;strong&gt;languages, libraries and frameworks&lt;/strong&gt; which are being used to build software applications, because they are the components I&amp;rsquo;m most familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Suppose your company needs to build a new software service which is going to be offered as an API. You will need to pick a &lt;strong&gt;language&lt;/strong&gt; (for example &lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt;), possibly &lt;strong&gt;a web framework&lt;/strong&gt; (like &lt;strong&gt;Django&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Flask&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;FastAPI&lt;/strong&gt;) and some additional &lt;strong&gt;libraries&lt;/strong&gt; (like &lt;strong&gt;SQLAlchemy&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;requests&lt;/strong&gt;, etc&amp;hellip;) to build your service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually developers will pick the tools they are most familiar with, or the tools which are most popular in the community, but very few people ask themselves: &lt;strong&gt;who is behind these tools? Who is maintaining them? Who is fixing the bugs? Who is adding new features?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And most importantly: &lt;strong&gt;how are these people being paid?&lt;/strong&gt; (You are not expecting them to work for free, right? 😏)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-current-funding-models&#34;&gt;The current funding models
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some languages and frameworks have a no profit foundation behind them (ie: &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.python.org&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.python.org/psf-landing/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python Software Foundation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.djangoproject.com&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Django&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.djangoproject.com/foundation/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Django Software Foundation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, etc.) which are responsible for managing the project and the community around it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They can receive a lot of &lt;strong&gt;independent donations&lt;/strong&gt; or being &lt;strong&gt;funded by big companies&lt;/strong&gt; like Google or Microsoft (ie: &lt;strong&gt;Guido Van Rossum&lt;/strong&gt;, the creator of &lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt;, was previously working for Google and now he is currently working for Microsoft).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big companies&lt;/strong&gt; (those earning billions every year) usually don&amp;rsquo;t have any problem spending some money to sustain the tools they also use, but this also means they &lt;strong&gt;can have a big influence on the direction&lt;/strong&gt; the project is taking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some smaller projects (like &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://fastapi.tiangolo.com&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;FastAPI&lt;/a&gt;) are being funded entirely by &lt;strong&gt;independent donations&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://fastapi.tiangolo.com/fastapi-people/#sponsors&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;https://fastapi.tiangolo.com/fastapi-people/#sponsors&lt;/a&gt; but this is not a sustainable model for the long term because there is no guarantee that the donations will keep coming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-venture-capital-model&#34;&gt;The Venture Capital model
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;A different way to fund open source projects is through private investors or &lt;strong&gt;venture capital&lt;/strong&gt;. For example &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://pydantic.dev&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;code&gt;pydantic&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a library which is also used by FastAPI) has recently received a &lt;strong&gt;$4.7 million investment&lt;/strong&gt; from a few VCs: &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://techcrunch.com/2023/02/16/sequoia-backs-open-source-data-validation-framework-pydantic-to-commercialize-with-cloud-services/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;https://techcrunch.com/2023/02/16/sequoia-backs-open-source-data-validation-framework-pydantic-to-commercialize-with-cloud-services/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another quite recent example (which has sparked a lot of discussions in the Python community) is the case of &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://astral.sh&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Astral&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a small company backed by VCs which are developing a couple of tools for the Python community: &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://astral.sh/ruff&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;code&gt;ruff&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which is a code linter and &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/astral-sh/uv&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;code&gt;uv&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which is a Python package and project manager written in &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.rust-lang.org&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rust&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-opinions-from-the-community&#34;&gt;The opinions from the Community
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;With specific regard to &lt;strong&gt;Astra&lt;/strong&gt;, there is an &lt;strong&gt;interesting conversation&lt;/strong&gt; happening in a &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://social.jacobian.org/@jacob@jacobian.org@jacob@jacobian.orgian.org/113091418140504394&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Mastodon thread&lt;/a&gt;, and from what I&amp;rsquo;ve seen, the &lt;strong&gt;opinions are quite divided&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of them are concerned because this company is using &lt;strong&gt;Rust&lt;/strong&gt; to implement these tools. This could cut Python developers out from directly contributing to the project, because they would need to learn a new language to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others are concerned because the company is backed by &lt;strong&gt;VCs&lt;/strong&gt;, and they &lt;strong&gt;could cut funds&lt;/strong&gt; at any time, leaving the project in an abandoned state. This of course is a valid concern, but since the project is open source, the community could fork it and continue the development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another issue that seems to be mentioned by a few people is the fact that Astral doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to have a &lt;strong&gt;clear business model&lt;/strong&gt; (at least until the time of this article). When asked directly, they have been vague about how they intend to monetize their projects and for this reason some &lt;strong&gt;people are being cautious before adopting their tools&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people are being optimistic instead and looking at this funding as a &lt;strong&gt;good thing&lt;/strong&gt;, because observing how quickly &lt;code&gt;ruff&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;uv&lt;/code&gt; have evolved in so little time, they recognise &lt;strong&gt;a lot can be done when people are allowed to work full time&lt;/strong&gt; on a project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-own-opinion&#34;&gt;My own opinion
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the specific case of &lt;code&gt;ruff&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;uv&lt;/code&gt;, I personally don&amp;rsquo;t have anything against the fact that they are written in Rust. My mantra is &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;use the right tool for the job&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;, and if Rust is the right tool for the job (according to their tests, linting the whole CPython code base &lt;strong&gt;only takes 0.16s&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;code&gt;ruff&lt;/code&gt;, while it takes &lt;strong&gt;11.63s&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;code&gt;flake8&lt;/code&gt; and even &lt;strong&gt;60s&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;code&gt;pylint&lt;/code&gt;), then so be it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, relying on &lt;strong&gt;VCs for funding is a double-edged sword&lt;/strong&gt;: on one side you now have a lot of money to hire people and let them work full time on the project. This ensures the &lt;strong&gt;development will proceed at fast pace&lt;/strong&gt; and issues will be addressed quickly. On the other side, other companies and community members could initially be attracted by the tool, decide to adopt features which are not available (nor compatible with) in other similar tools and &lt;strong&gt;eventually find themselves locked in a proprietary ecosystem&lt;/strong&gt; (check what recently happened to the data scientists community using &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.theregister.com/2024/08/08/anaconda_puts_the_squeeze_on/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anaconda&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-could-we-do-instead&#34;&gt;What could we do instead
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I think an alternative&lt;/strong&gt; and mid ground solution to the ones described above &lt;strong&gt;exists&lt;/strong&gt;: each company should &lt;strong&gt;fund the projects&lt;/strong&gt; they use and rely on most and / or they should &lt;strong&gt;allow employees&lt;/strong&gt; to dedicate some time to &lt;strong&gt;contribute back&lt;/strong&gt; to these projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;funding-projects&#34;&gt;Funding projects
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s pick for example the 5 top components a company could rely on: &lt;strong&gt;Python, FastAPI, SQLAlchemy, Pydantic and PostgreSQL&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company should allocate a yearly budget for these components and donate regularly to the projects. Many companies have no issues purchasing licenses and seats for the services they use, so why donating regularly should be a problem?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By having many companies donating to a project, &lt;strong&gt;we avoid that a single company has too much influence&lt;/strong&gt; on the direction of development. If a single company decides to stop funding a component, there would be many other continuing to support it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small projects (those with a single lead developer) could &lt;strong&gt;use the money&lt;/strong&gt; income to be able &lt;strong&gt;to work full time&lt;/strong&gt; on it. Larger projects could &lt;strong&gt;hire more people&lt;/strong&gt; to work full time. The necessary structure and organisation should reflect the size of the project itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would be a &lt;strong&gt;win win situation&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Developers&lt;/strong&gt; could &lt;strong&gt;work on something they love&lt;/strong&gt; and being paid for it. &lt;strong&gt;Companies&lt;/strong&gt; could trust the components they use even more because with people working full time on it, it&amp;rsquo;s more &lt;strong&gt;unlikely the project can be abandoned&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is quite similar to the funding model of &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.django-rest-framework.org/#funding&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Django Rest Framework&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;allowing-employees-to-contribute-back&#34;&gt;Allowing employees to contribute back
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes project owners need some direct help fixing bugs, preparing releases etc&amp;hellip; another way of contribute could be &lt;strong&gt;allowing employees to dedicate some work time to contribute back&lt;/strong&gt; directly. This can have multiple advantages: employees can &lt;strong&gt;work on something fun&lt;/strong&gt; and they can &lt;strong&gt;learn new things&lt;/strong&gt; (reminder: often employees leave a company because they want to work on more interesting stuff and because they are not learning enough in their current role) while &lt;strong&gt;projects&lt;/strong&gt; can &lt;strong&gt;get additional&lt;/strong&gt; (even if not regular) &lt;strong&gt;help&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m convinced &lt;strong&gt;a more sustainable way for funding open source projects is possible&lt;/strong&gt;. As &lt;strong&gt;software developers&lt;/strong&gt; we &lt;strong&gt;can have an high impact on companies&lt;/strong&gt; (spreading the word, speaking at conferences, leading by example etc&amp;hellip;) and this can be beneficial both for the longevity of existing projects and for the safety of companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; think about this possibility?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>UDS happening online only: pros and cons</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/uds-happening-online-only-pros-and-cons/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/uds-happening-online-only-pros-and-cons/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When last week &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://fridge.ubuntu.com/2013/02/26/ubuntu-developer-summits-now-online-and-every-three-months/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Canonical announced&lt;/a&gt;
the usual UDS was not going to happen I was a bit shocked and
disappointed: starting from the next UDS (that is going to happen
tomorrow!) the event will be &lt;strong&gt;online only&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;every 3 months&lt;/strong&gt;.
During these days I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking a lot about this move and I will
tell you what are the pros and cons, in my opinion, followed by some
final thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pros&#34;&gt;Pros
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Having 4 UDS every year, instead of 2, is surely a better thing. I&amp;rsquo;m a
big fan of Scrum methodology, so I think that &lt;strong&gt;iterating more often is
better&lt;/strong&gt; than iterating less. If there are any mistakes you can correct
them and iterating again before releasing the final product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Potentially &lt;strong&gt;more people can partecipate&lt;/strong&gt; to the event (even the
opposite is true and I will explain why). People won&amp;rsquo;t need to move from
home, travel, pay any expense etc&amp;hellip; they just need a computer and a
good Internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;cheaper for everyone&lt;/strong&gt;: I can just imagine how expensive could be
for Canonical to organize a similar event. Booking a big hotel, paying
travel and expenses to near one houndred of community people. People who
didn&amp;rsquo;t get any sponsorization had to pay all the travel expenses to
attend the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cons&#34;&gt;Cons
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Potentially &lt;strong&gt;less people can partecipate&lt;/strong&gt; to the event. Yes, like I
said before even this sentence is true and I will explain why. First of
all, using Google+ there are at least three countries that will be cut
out: &lt;strong&gt;China&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Thailand&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Vietnam&lt;/strong&gt;. Google+ is not available
in those countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you sure that special people will be able to follow the event? For
example &lt;strong&gt;blind people&lt;/strong&gt; won&amp;rsquo;t be able to chat or to ask question in the
chat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Only 10 people&lt;/strong&gt; will be able to talk. In normal UDS sessions more
people could raise the hand and ask a question or interact with the
track leaders. Who will choose the 10 people with audio+video streaming
rights?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will &lt;strong&gt;completly miss the social aspect&lt;/strong&gt; of the UDS. If you think
this was only a secondary part, please go on. I felt more committed to
work and collaborate with people I met in person than with someone I&amp;rsquo;ve
never met before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Announcing an event, even if online, just &lt;strong&gt;one week before&lt;/strong&gt; it
happens. Really? Some people had already taken vacation from work,
booked flights etc&amp;hellip; not counting many people that can&amp;rsquo;t take 2 days
off from work just with 1 week notice period. It&amp;rsquo;s also almost
impossible that community members have the time to schedule a blueprint
and be able to discuss about a subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final thoughts
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;From a &lt;strong&gt;cutting costs&lt;/strong&gt; point of view I really can&amp;rsquo;t say anything.
Organizing UDS was surely very expensive for Canonical and nobody can
blame them if they decided to spend those money in a different way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What really concerns me: is UDS still useful? My opinion is that at
least since latest 2 or 3 UDS the presence of the Community was not so
relevant, because I had &lt;strong&gt;the clear sensation that the most important
decisions were made by Canonical before the UDS&lt;/strong&gt; and then there was
just some details tuning. Another proof of my thoughts is the today
announcement: &lt;strong&gt;despite the fact that I 100% agree with Unity switching
to Qt/QML&lt;/strong&gt; (I already proposed this 2 years ago during Budapest UDS,
but nobody listened to me) &lt;strong&gt;I completly disagree with the way the
decision was made&lt;/strong&gt;: not a single involvement or discussion with the
community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would apreaciate &lt;strong&gt;more openness and honesty&lt;/strong&gt; from Canonical. Do you
want to take all the decisions? That&amp;rsquo;s fine, but at least state it
clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Last.fm: the money music revolution!</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/lastfm-the-money-music-revolution/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/lastfm-the-money-music-revolution/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/lastfm-the-money-music-revolution/lastfm.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;300&#34;
	height=&#34;255&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;lastfm&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;117&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;282px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non c&amp;rsquo;è alcun errore nel titolo di questo post. Sebbene lo slogan originale di
&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lastfm.it&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Last.fm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; fosse &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;The Social Music
Revolution&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;, ho voluto modificarlo in questo modo, per sottolineare il
recente cambiamento di rotta di un servizio che fino a pochi giorni fa
ritenevo uno dei migliori, se non il migliore, del suo genere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facciamo un passo indietro per spiegare cos&amp;rsquo;è Last.fm. Si tratta di un
servizio che permette, una volta registrati, di condividere le canzoni
che ascoltiamo (titolo e autore, non il file audio) in modo che si possa
essere messi in contatto con altre persone che ascoltano i nostri gruppi
preferiti oppure di ricevere suggerimenti su gruppi simili a quelli che
ascoltiamo. Grazie a questa funzione ho avuto la possibilità di
conoscere ed apprezzare gruppi musicali di cui prima ignoravo
l&amp;rsquo;esistenza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oltre a permettere lo scrobbling (invio del titolo della canzone) e la
creazione automatica di classifiche, il sito mette a disposizione
moltissimi strumenti che hanno permesso la creazione di una vasta
community musicale. La community, grazie a questi strumenti, ha
arricchito il sito web di moltissimi dati importanti: un wiki con i dati
dei gruppi musicali, i tag su ogni canzone, gruppi di discussione e la
creazione di eventi e ritrovi. Last.fm è anche una &amp;ldquo;radio&amp;rdquo;, ma in un
modo un po&amp;rsquo; diverso rispetto a quello a cui siamo abituati.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non esistono playlist valide per tutti gli utenti, ogni utente ha la
propria playlist, in base ai brani ascoltati, ai gruppi simili ed ai
suggerimenti degli amici. Oltre alle proprie playlista è inoltre
possibile ascoltare quelle dei &amp;ldquo;vicini&amp;rdquo;, degli amici e dei gruppi ai
quali siamo iscritti. Se oggi Last.Fm è diventata quello che tutti
vediamo, è in gran parte grazie al lavoro svolto dalla community
musicale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Che cosa è successo per portarmi alla decisione di &lt;strong&gt;eliminare il mio
account&lt;/strong&gt;, vecchio di &lt;strong&gt;3 anni&lt;/strong&gt;, con piu&amp;rsquo; di &lt;strong&gt;30.000&lt;/strong&gt; brani
ascoltati?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circa un mese fa i vertici di Last.fm hanno deciso che entro poco tempo
il servizio di radio in streaming sarebbee diventato a pagamento, a
causa dell&amp;rsquo;aumento dei costi di licenza imposti dalle major. Per
continuare ad ascoltare la radio &lt;strong&gt;si dovranno pagare 3€ al mese&lt;/strong&gt;.
Quello che ha scatenato l&amp;rsquo;ira di moltissimi utenti e che mi ha fatto
prendere la decisione di disiscrivermi, è il fatto che &lt;strong&gt;USA&lt;/strong&gt;,
&lt;strong&gt;Inghilterra&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;Germania&lt;/strong&gt; potranno continuare ad usufruire
&lt;strong&gt;gratuitamente&lt;/strong&gt; del servizio. Questa divisione in paesi di serie A e
paesi di serie B non è piaciuta proprio a nessuno, basta guardare le
&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://blog.last.fm/2009/04/22/radio-subscriptions&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;centinaia di commenti&lt;/a&gt; che sono
arrivati sul blog ufficiale di Last.fm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Io mi associo al pensiero comune: se anche USA, Inghilterra e Germania
pagassero, il costo potrebbe scendere a 1 o 2 euro al mese ed inoltre
non ci sarebbero divisioni e/o discriminazioni a seconda del paese di
provenienza. Avrei pagato volentier anche &lt;strong&gt;3€/mese&lt;/strong&gt; se non ci fossero
state queste differenze. Perchè gli altri paesi devono pagare pochi
privilegiati?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mio parere Last.fm ha commesso un gravissimo errore facendo questa
mossa e sono convinto che entro breve perderà moltissimi utenti
smettendo inoltre di essere una community ricca di contenuti creati
dagli utenti stessi. Staremo a vedere se ci saranno inversioni di rotta
o se continueranno a seguire questa strada.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Diventa un Ubuntero!</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/diventa-un-ubuntero/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/diventa-un-ubuntero/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/diventa-un-ubuntero/ubuntu_circle_trasparent.png&#34;
	width=&#34;174&#34;
	height=&#34;170&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;ubuntu\_circle\_trasparent.png&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;102&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;245px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vorrei segnalarvi un sito web che forse molti di voi conosceranno già: &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://launchpad.net/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;https://launchpad.net/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
è un sito messo in piedi dalla Canonical (la società che finanzia lo
sviluppo di Ubuntu) e presenta alcune funzioni molto interessanti:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;code&#34;&gt;Code
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;è possibile pubblicare qui una propria patch ad un programma,
in modo che gli sviluppatori la possano unire al codice ufficiale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bugs&#34;&gt;Bugs
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;un modulo per segnalare i bug della Ubuntu e degli altri
progetti che sono registrati su launchpad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;blueprints&#34;&gt;Blueprints
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;il posto dove pubblicare le proprie idee, proposte di
miglioramento, suggerimenti sulle future funzionalità ecc&amp;hellip;. della
Ubuntu. Se avete un&amp;rsquo;idea originale per una funziona che ancora non è
presente in Ubuntu, potete scriverla qui.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;translations&#34;&gt;Translations
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;consente di visualizzare le stringhe ed i messaggi non
ancora tradotti dei programmi di Ubuntu e permette di scrivere la
propria traduzione, nella lingua desiderata. La traduzione verrà poi
sottoposta ad approvazione. Un ottimo modo per suddividersi il lavoro di
traduzione dei vari programmi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;answers&#34;&gt;Answers
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;qui è possibile fare domande (come su un forum) e
rispondere alle domande che ancora sono &amp;ldquo;open&amp;rdquo; (cioè senza risposta).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tutti i contributi che date in una di queste sezioni, vanno ad aumentare
il vostro &amp;ldquo;karma&amp;rdquo;, ovvero la notorietà, la popolarità e l&amp;rsquo;importanza
all&amp;rsquo;interno della community di Ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La mia pagina ad esempio è questa: &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://launchpad.net/%7Eandy80&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;https://launchpad.net/~andy80&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Se non vi sentite ancora dei programmatori esperti, ma volete comunque
far qualcosa per migliorare la Ubuntu (o altri progetti registrati in
quel sito), quello è il posto giusto nel quale spendere un po&amp;rsquo; del
proprio tempo.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
