<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Andrea Grandi - Canonical</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/</link><description>Software Developer</description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2013 01:09:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>UDS happening online only: pros and cons</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2013/03/05/uds-happening-online-only-pros-and-cons/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When last week &lt;a href="http://fridge.ubuntu.com/2013/02/26/ubuntu-developer-summits-now-online-and-every-three-months/"&gt;Canonical
announced&lt;/a&gt;
the usual UDS was not going to happen I was a bit shocked and
disappointed: starting from the next UDS (that is going to happen
tomorrow!) the event will be &lt;strong&gt;online only&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;every 3 months&lt;/strong&gt;.
During these days I've been thinking a lot about this move and I will
tell you what are the pros and cons, in my opinion, followed by some
final thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pros&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having 4 UDS every year, instead of 2, is surely a better thing. I'm a
big fan of Scrum methodology, so I think that &lt;strong&gt;iterating more often is
better&lt;/strong&gt; than iterating less. If there are any mistakes you can correct
them and iterating again before releasing the final product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Potentially &lt;strong&gt;more people can partecipate&lt;/strong&gt; to the event (even the
opposite is true and I will explain why). People won't need to move from
home, travel, pay any expense etc... they just need a computer and a
good Internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's &lt;strong&gt;cheaper for everyone&lt;/strong&gt;: I can just imagine how expensive could be
for Canonical to organize a similar event. Booking a big hotel, paying
travel and expenses to near one houndred of community people. People who
didn't get any sponsorization had to pay all the travel expenses to
attend the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Potentially &lt;strong&gt;less people can partecipate&lt;/strong&gt; to the event. Yes, like I
said before even this sentence is true and I will explain why. First of
all, using Google+ there are at least three countries that will be cut
out: &lt;strong&gt;China&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Thailand&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Vietnam&lt;/strong&gt;. Google+ is not available
in those countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you sure that special people will be able to follow the event? For
example &lt;strong&gt;blind people&lt;/strong&gt; won't be able to chat or to ask question in the
chat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Only 10 people&lt;/strong&gt; will be able to talk. In normal UDS sessions more
people could raise the hand and ask a question or interact with the
track leaders. Who will choose the 10 people with audio+video streaming
rights?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will &lt;strong&gt;completly miss the social aspect&lt;/strong&gt; of the UDS. If you think
this was only a secondary part, please go on. I felt more committed to
work and collaborate with people I met in person than with someone I've
never met before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Announcing an event, even if online, just &lt;strong&gt;one week before&lt;/strong&gt; it
happens. Really? Some people had already taken vacation from work,
booked flights etc... not counting many people that can't take 2 days
off from work just with 1 week notice period. It's also almost
impossible that community members have the time to schedule a blueprint
and be able to discuss about a subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a &lt;strong&gt;cutting costs&lt;/strong&gt; point of view I really can't say anything.
Organizing UDS was surely very expensive for Canonical and nobody can
blame them if they decided to spend those money in a different way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What really concerns me: is UDS still useful? My opinion is that at
least since latest 2 or 3 UDS the presence of the Community was not so
relevant, because I had &lt;strong&gt;the clear sensation that the most important
decisions were made by Canonical before the UDS&lt;/strong&gt; and then there was
just some details tuning. Another proof of my thoughts is the today
announcement: &lt;strong&gt;despite the fact that I 100% agree with Unity switching
to Qt/QML&lt;/strong&gt; (I already proposed this 2 years ago during Budapest UDS,
but nobody listened to me) &lt;strong&gt;I completly disagree with the way the
decision was made&lt;/strong&gt;: not a single involvement or discussion with the
community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would apreaciate &lt;strong&gt;more openness and honesty&lt;/strong&gt; from Canonical. Do you
want to take all the decisions? That's fine, but at least state it
clearly.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2013 01:09:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2013-03-05:/2013/03/05/uds-happening-online-only-pros-and-cons/</guid><category>Ubuntu (EN), UDS</category><category>Canonical</category><category>community</category><category>Linux</category><category>meeting</category><category>Ubuntu</category><category>UDS</category></item><item><title>UDS day-1</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2011/05/11/uds-day-1/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.andreagrandi.it/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/IMG_0286.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.andreagrandi.it/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/IMG_0286-300x200.jpg" title="IMG_0286"&gt;{.alignright
.size-medium .wp-image-528 width="240"
height="160"}&lt;/a&gt;My
day started at 7:30 with a &lt;strong&gt;very nice breakfast!&lt;/strong&gt; I was alone with
just another guy this morning, in a very big breakbast room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After it I grabbed my badge to avoid queue later and went back to my
room to wake up &lt;strong&gt;Marco Trevisan&lt;/strong&gt; (he was still sleeping :P ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The keynote was opened by &lt;strong&gt;Jono Bacon&lt;/strong&gt; (the Ubuntu Community manager),
followed by Ubuntu founder &lt;strong&gt;Mark Shuttleworth&lt;/strong&gt;. The most interesting
(and tweeted) part of the keynote was "&lt;strong&gt;how to prounounce Oneiric&lt;/strong&gt;"
(Oeniric will be the next Ubuntu release).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The keynote finished with a bit late, so all the other tracks were
shifted forward. I followed "&lt;strong&gt;Unity 2D Oneiric Improvements&lt;/strong&gt;", it was
interesting because there were some &lt;strong&gt;Nokia/Qt&lt;/strong&gt; guys and they looked
very interested in helping the Unity 2D team and collaborating with
them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now following "&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/DocumentationTeam/SystemDocumentation/Tasks/Oneiric"&gt;Shaping a strategy for Ubuntu user
assistance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;",
I just had the possibility my involvement into helping people that
require Ubuntu assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;lunch&lt;/strong&gt; has been very tasty, I had the possibility to eat some
local recipes, not bad at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After lunch we had a short session on &lt;strong&gt;Qt&lt;/strong&gt;. The version 4.8 is going
to be released in a couple of months, while 5.0 is announced to be
released in 1 year from now: it will be almost code-compatible with 4.x,
it will have an improved support for Qt Quick and QML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As last track of the day I decided to follow "&lt;strong&gt;Personal Cloud&lt;/strong&gt;". Not a
perfect track, since the person who should have been here was only
talking with us using Skype and it was more difficoult to hear what he
said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of this day there was the "&lt;strong&gt;Meet &amp;amp; Greet&lt;/strong&gt;" party, sponsored
by Freescale and Openstack. They offered a dinner and we had some good
music after it.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2011 11:05:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2011-05-11:/2011/05/11/uds-day-1/</guid><category>Ubuntu (EN), UDS</category><category>Budapest</category><category>Canonical</category><category>conference</category><category>Ubuntu</category><category>UDS</category></item></channel></rss>