<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Andrea Grandi - discount</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2009 15:05:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Questions/Answers about Nokia N900 and Discounted Device Program</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2009/11/12/questionsanswers-about-nokia-n900-and-discounted-device-program/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Being one of the developers who received the discount to buy a N900,
during these days I contacted the DDP customer care to have more
informations and details. I'll publish here both my original question
and the official reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) The price of N900 is 250€ and I've read of people who paid it this
price. Anyway here you say that the VAT is not included:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://pro.forum.nokia.com/site/global/tech_resources/discounted_devices/l_ddp.jsp"&gt;https://pro.forum.nokia.com/site/global/tech_resources/discounted_devices/l_ddp.jsp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
so it should costs 300€ not 250€, right?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The VAT applies only for Finnish developers, for the others the price is
the price they see in the eStore, no VAT is added to that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So, all non-finnish european people, will pay &lt;strong&gt;250€&lt;/strong&gt; for the N900.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) How much time can I wait before ordering it? In this moment I'm in
Valencia (Spain) and I won't come back to Italy before Christmas. I'd
like the order to be shipped to my home in Italy (I registered as
italian user and I want italian keyboard layout), but I'd like to wait
to order it, because since there's no warranty and I need to tell you
about any problem within a week, if I order it now I will be able to
check it only at the end of december when I'll come back to Italy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess this should not be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This part is not confirmed yet, since Quim told us to hurry up to buy
it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3) How many devices can I buy at that price? Here you say I can
buy two:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://pro.forum.nokia.com/site/global/tech_resources/discounted_devices/l_ddp.jsp"&gt;https://pro.forum.nokia.com/site/global/tech_resources/discounted_devices/l_ddp.jsp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
but here you say I can buy one:
&lt;a href="https://pro.forum.nokia.com/showProduct.do?product_id=5096"&gt;https://pro.forum.nokia.com/showProduct.do?product_id=5096&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want two devices, but another friend of mine, who help me in a
project for the Maemo Community, would like to be able to buy one for
the same price (he wasn't able to get the discount because his karma is
still low).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I know, you can only purchase 1x device per person, regarding
MAEMO N900.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4) Where can we find the new firmware? In the FAQ you say: DDP does
not flash devices. It's ok, I can do it, but there's no public firmware
for N900 at the moment.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To update N900, can possibly be using NSU. Nokia software updater.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5) Is it possible to have a device with localized keyboard (for
example italian one) ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All N900 will have EURO variant, Italian language is one option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; even these replies come from the official customer care, I
don't assume any responsability if they shouldn't be all exact. If you
have any doubt, please contact them directly at
&lt;strong&gt;[DDP.program@nokia.com]{}&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2009 15:05:00 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2009-11-12:/2009/11/12/questionsanswers-about-nokia-n900-and-discounted-device-program/</guid><category>Maemo (EN)</category><category>DDP</category><category>discount</category><category>maemo</category><category>N900</category><category>nokia</category></item></channel></rss>