<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Andrea Grandi - Igalia</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2009 15:44:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>Writing Python bindings of existing C libraries – (2) – A simple example of binding</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2009/08/06/writing-python-bindings-of-existing-c-libraries-%e2%80%93-2-%e2%80%93-a-simple-example-of-binding/</link><description>&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I promised in the preceding post, I'll provide a very easy example of
a python binding. Let's suppose we don't want to use the methods
included in Python to sum two integer values and we want to do it in C
and then call the add method from a python script. I'll write the
complete source code first and then I'll explain all the parts of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Source Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[sourcecode language="C"]&lt;br&gt;
#include &amp;lt;Python.h&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;static PyObject *foo_add(PyObject *self, PyObject *args)&lt;br&gt;
{&lt;br&gt;
int a;&lt;br&gt;
int b;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if (!PyArg_ParseTuple(args, "ii", &amp;amp;a, &amp;amp;b))&lt;br&gt;
{&lt;br&gt;
return NULL;&lt;br&gt;
}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;return Py_BuildValue("i", a + b);&lt;br&gt;
}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;static PyMethodDef foo_methods[] = {&lt;br&gt;
{ "add", (PyCFunction)foo_add, METH_VARARGS, NULL },&lt;br&gt;
{ NULL, NULL, 0, NULL }&lt;br&gt;
};&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PyMODINIT_FUNC initfoo()&lt;br&gt;
{&lt;br&gt;
Py_InitModule3("foo", foo_methods, "My first extension module.");&lt;br&gt;
}&lt;br&gt;
[/sourcecode]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How it works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all we have to include &lt;strong&gt;Python.h&lt;/strong&gt; in our C file. This allows
us to write an extension for Python language. To be able to include this
header, we must have the python development packages installed in our
system. For example in Debian based distributions we can install them
with this command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install python2.5-dev&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every module has at least three parts. In the first part we write
methods we want to call from the final python module: in this case we
have a method called &lt;strong&gt;foo_add&lt;/strong&gt; where "&lt;em&gt;foo&lt;/em&gt;" is the name of the
module and "&lt;em&gt;add&lt;/em&gt;" the name of the method. Every method is declared as
&lt;strong&gt;static PyObject&lt;/strong&gt;. The method does anything particular except calling
PyArg_ParseTuple to validate the input (we'll discuss this later),
adding the two passed numbers and returning the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second part we have something like a dictionary, defined as
static &lt;strong&gt;PyMethodDef&lt;/strong&gt; and called foo_methods (where "foo" again is the
name of the module). For each method we want to expose in our python
module, we have to add something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;{"add", (PyCFunction)foo_add, METH_VARARGS, NULL}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where "&lt;em&gt;add&lt;/em&gt;" is the name of the method we want to be visible in our
module, &lt;em&gt;(PyCFunction)foo_add&lt;/em&gt; is a pointer to our foo_add method,
implemented in the C module, METH_VARARGS means that we want to pass
some parameters to the function and the last one would be the
description of the method (we can leave it NULL if we want).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third part allows us to register the defined method/s and the module:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Py_InitModule3("foo", foo_methods, "My first extension module.");&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Parsing Parameters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;PyArg_ParseTuple&lt;/strong&gt; function extracts arguments from the
&lt;strong&gt;PyObject&lt;/strong&gt; passed as parameter to the current method and follows
almost the sscanf syntax to parse parameters (in this case we had &lt;em&gt;"ii"&lt;/em&gt;
for two integers). You can fin the complete reference here:
&lt;a href="http://docs.python.org/c-api/arg.html"&gt;http://docs.python.org/c-api/arg.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Building and installing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To build the module, we have to be in the source directory and execute
this command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gcc -shared -I/usr/include/python2.5 foo.c -o foo.so&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;then we've to copy the generated module to the python's modules
directory:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;cp foo.so /usr/lib/python2.5/site-packages/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Testing our module&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Testing the module is really easy. We've to start a python shell or
create a python script with the following source code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[sourcecode language="python"]&lt;br&gt;
import foo&lt;br&gt;
print foo.add(2, 3)&lt;br&gt;
[/sourcecode]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if all is working fine, the printed result should be &lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://docs.python.org/extending/extending.html"&gt;http://docs.python.org/extending/extending.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.wrox.com/WileyCDA/WroxTitle/productCd-0764596543.html"&gt;http://www.wrox.com/WileyCDA/WroxTitle/productCd-0764596543.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div id="_mcePaste"
style="overflow: hidden; position: absolute; left: -10000px; top: 399px; width: 1px; height: 1px;"&gt;

python2.5-dev

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="_mcePaste"
style="overflow: hidden; position: absolute; left: -10000px; top: 399px; width: 1px; height: 1px;"&gt;

python2.5-dev

&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2009 15:44:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2009-08-06:/2009/08/06/writing-python-bindings-of-existing-c-libraries-%e2%80%93-2-%e2%80%93-a-simple-example-of-binding/</guid><category>HowTo, Igalia, Linux, Maemo (EN), Programmazione, Python</category><category>binding</category><category>Igalia</category><category>maemo</category><category>Python</category></item><item><title>Writing Python bindings of existing C libraries - (1) - Introduction</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2009/08/03/writing-python-bindings-of-existing-c-libraries-1-introduction/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This summer I'm having the pleasure of working in
&lt;a href="http://www.igalia.com"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Igalia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a spanish free software company)
for a couple of months and they assigned me to an interesting project:
developing &lt;strong&gt;Python bindings&lt;/strong&gt; for &lt;strong&gt;MAFW&lt;/strong&gt; library (a &lt;strong&gt;Maemo&lt;/strong&gt;
multimedia library that will be used in &lt;strong&gt;Fremantle&lt;/strong&gt; release).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the opportunity to work both with &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt; (yes, Python bindings are
almost C code) and &lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt; (it's a good practice to write unittest of
all implemented methods) it's a good way to improve my knowledges in
both languages and since I wasn't able to find much documentation about
these kind of things, I'm going to share my own experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is a Binding?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A binding is a Python module, written in C language, that allows Python
developers to call functions from existing C libraries from their python
applications. It's just like a "&lt;em&gt;bridge&lt;/em&gt;" from C world to Python one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why writing bindings?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of reasons to write python bindings instead of
writing a library in python language from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all I don't think is good duplicating code, so if a library
already exists and it's written in C, why writing it again in another
language? There's no reason. A lot of code already exist in C world and
all we have to do is to create a bridge with python world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another good reason, in particular when a C library doesn't exist yet,
is the fact that python code is slower than C code for some tasks (for
example multimedia codecs). In these cases is good to implement the core
library in C language and then create a python binding for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coming next&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the title of this post says, this is only an introduction to the
subjects I'm going to write about. If you have any particular request
about any argument you would like to read, please feel free to leave me
a comment. Next posts will talk about these things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A simple example of binding:&lt;/strong&gt; I'll write a simple library in C
    language and I'll show how to create the relative python binding,
    providing complete source code and an example for python developers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building and installing python bindings with distutils:&lt;/strong&gt; I'll
    explain how to use &lt;strong&gt;distutils&lt;/strong&gt; to build and install the binding
    (using the well know method "python setup.py install").&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defining new types:&lt;/strong&gt; this post will be about how to write new
    types in C language and being able to use them from python code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using codegen to write bindings:&lt;/strong&gt; I'll explain how to use
    &lt;strong&gt;codegen&lt;/strong&gt; utils to automate lot of tasks, to generate the most
    part of binding code and how to customize the generated code using
    overrides.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2009 10:04:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2009-08-03:/2009/08/03/writing-python-bindings-of-existing-c-libraries-1-introduction/</guid><category>HowTo, Igalia, Linux, Maemo (EN), Programmazione, Python</category><category>bindings</category><category>C</category><category>Igalia</category><category>libraries</category><category>library</category><category>maemo</category><category>pymaemo</category><category>Python</category></item><item><title>I officially joined the PyMaemo team</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2009/07/25/i-officially-joined-the-pymaemo-team/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This summer I'm working for 2 months at &lt;a href="http://www.igalia.com"&gt;Igalia&lt;/a&gt;,
a spanish free software company, and they assigned me the project of
writing a &lt;strong&gt;Python binding&lt;/strong&gt; for &lt;strong&gt;MAFW&lt;/strong&gt; (a new multimedia library that
will be included in &lt;strong&gt;Freemantle&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After few days I discovered that
&lt;a href="http://garage.maemo.org/projects/pymaemo/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PyMaemo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; team was
already working to it, so I asked to join them and they accepted me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really love Python language and since I think other developers love it
too, I think we should provide good bindings for every library available
in Maemo, so lot of developers can start writing their applications in
this language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll work to this project full time until the first week of september,
so I hope to be able to learn a lot and to contribute as much as I can
to this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone else want to join PyMaemo team and help us to develop Python
bindings, I think he will be welcome!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2009 13:54:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2009-07-25:/2009/07/25/i-officially-joined-the-pymaemo-team/</guid><category>Igalia, Linux, Maemo (EN), Programmazione, Python</category><category>bindings</category><category>freemantle</category><category>Igalia</category><category>maemo</category><category>Python</category></item></channel></rss>