<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Andrea Grandi - MeeGo</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Jul 2010 16:31:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>Announcing mSoma: Maemo/MeeGo client for SomaFM</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2010/07/03/announcing-msoma-maemomeego-client-for-somafm/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://somafm.com"&gt;SomaFM&lt;/a&gt; is a streaming radio with near 16 different
channels, available for free. Even if it's possible to copy-paste their
streaming URLs to N900 Media Player, we
(&lt;a href="http://maemo.org/profile/view/andy80"&gt;me&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://maemo.org/profile/view/lorebett"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lorenzo
Bettini&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) decided to create a
custom application, to make channels switching easier for the end user
and to be able to add more features. We decided to take advantage of the
new &lt;strong&gt;Nokia SDK&lt;/strong&gt; and write the application in Qt/C++. Source code is
available on &lt;a href="http://gitorious.org/msoma"&gt;Gitorious&lt;/a&gt; and it's always
updated with latest version we're working on. If someone want to test
the application, it's available in &lt;strong&gt;extras-devel&lt;/strong&gt; repository  ("msoma"
under Multimedia section) of N900.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_380" align="aligncenter" width="389"
caption="mSoma"]&lt;a href="http://www.andreagrandi.it/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/msoma_0.1.2.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.andreagrandi.it/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/msoma_0.1.2.png" title="msoma_0.1.2"&gt;{.size-full
.wp-image-380 width="389"
height="233"}&lt;/a&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UI is still in development as you can see. The application is
already usable, but of course we have to work hard on the user
interface. Feel free to test/use it and send us any feedback. If you
want to contribute to our project (coders are welcome) please send us a
patch with your code or ask us to be added to mSoma development team in
Gitorious.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jul 2010 16:31:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2010-07-03:/2010/07/03/announcing-msoma-maemomeego-client-for-somafm/</guid><category>maemo</category><category>MeeGo</category><category>N900</category><category>nokia</category><category>Qt</category><category>SomaFM</category></item><item><title>Twitter client for Maemo in Qt + Python: call for developers and UI designers</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2010/02/22/twitter-client-for-maemo-in-qt-python-call-for-developers-and-ui-designers/</link><description>&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name's &lt;strong&gt;Andrea Grandi&lt;/strong&gt;, I'm italian and I'm a Maemo
user/lover/contributor since the &lt;strong&gt;Nokia 770&lt;/strong&gt;. I love &lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt; as
development language and few months ago I also gave some contributions
to the &lt;a href="http://pymaemo.garage.maemo.org/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PyMaemo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these days I had the idea to start writing a &lt;strong&gt;Twitter&lt;/strong&gt; client for
&lt;strong&gt;Maemo&lt;/strong&gt; with a precise direction in my mind. I'll try to explain all
my reasons here. First of all I've to thank the author of
&lt;a href="http://mauku.henrikhedberg.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mauku&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; client. I use it since its
first version and I'm quite happy with it. Then, why do I want to write
another one?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maemo&lt;/strong&gt; (MeeGo) is moving to &lt;strong&gt;Qt&lt;/strong&gt; and for this reason I'm going
    to use Qt, while Mauku uses Gtk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm learning Qt and what is better than writing a complete (but not
    too complex) application to learn better?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mauku is not free as lot of people could think. Reading the source
    codeyou find this "You are NOT allowed to modify or redistribute the
    source code.", while I want to write a client and release it under
    &lt;strong&gt;GPL2&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;GPL3&lt;/strong&gt; license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mauku is not updated since some months and we have no news about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I love Python and I like to write free software in this language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to give to Maemo a stronger contribute.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My request for help&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before lot of people start writing their own client resulting in 4-5
twitter clients for Maemo, why don't we join our strength and work to a
common project? I'm not a Python expert nor a Qt one, but I've some
experience as project/team leader and since this is not a complex
project, I would be glad to lead it. So, I'm looking for Python
developers, Qt developers, UI designers and whoever want to contribute
to this project. I still have to find a good name and logo for this
application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who want to help me?&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2010 17:16:00 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2010-02-22:/2010/02/22/twitter-client-for-maemo-in-qt-python-call-for-developers-and-ui-designers/</guid><category>maemo</category><category>MeeGo</category><category>N900</category><category>nokia</category><category>Python</category><category>Qt</category><category>twitter</category></item><item><title>Nokia N900: reboot loop after PR 1.1.1 upgrade is not a firmware bug</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2010/02/20/nokia-n900-reboot-loop-after-pr-1-1-1-upgrade-is-not-a-firmware-bug/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Few days ago I published &lt;a href="http://www.andreagrandi.it/2010/02/17/nokia-n900-some-problems-with-latest-pr-1-1-1-firmware/"&gt;some
notes&lt;/a&gt;
about my personal experience with &lt;strong&gt;PR 1.1.1&lt;/strong&gt; firmware upgrade in Nokia
&lt;strong&gt;N900&lt;/strong&gt;. In particular my device got an infinite reboot loop after
upgrading the firmware and I had to flash the firmware image from
scratch to fix the problem. Today I was kindly contacted by &lt;strong&gt;Max
Waterman&lt;/strong&gt; (I suppose he works for Nokia) and he explained me what was
the problem. It was caused by a little bug in Harmattan UI demo and they
fixed it (the fix is already available in extras-devel).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No surprise for me: extras-devel contains unstable packages and if user
enables it, he does at his own risk. The most important thing is the
fact that the official firmware without any unstable application doesn't
suffer of this problem at all. The thing that really impressed me so
much (in a positive sense) it's that I was contacted privately by a
Nokia developer apologizing for the bug (no problem man, it's part of
the game if someone want to test extras-devel software) and explaining
that they already fixed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what I like of Maemo (or should I already call it MeeGo?), I
really feel to be a part of it!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2010 02:50:00 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2010-02-20:/2010/02/20/nokia-n900-reboot-loop-after-pr-1-1-1-upgrade-is-not-a-firmware-bug/</guid><category>firmware</category><category>maemo</category><category>MeeGo</category><category>N900</category><category>nokia</category></item></channel></rss>