<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Andrea Grandi - music</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/</link><description>Software Developer</description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2015 10:10:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Soma.fm + Spotify + import.io + Python mashup: automatically create a Spotify playlist with Soma.fm tracks</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2015/07/12/soma-fm-spotify-import-io-python-mashup/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm a big fan of &lt;a href="http://somafm.com"&gt;Soma.fm&lt;/a&gt; (a 25+ channels streaming
radio based in San Francisco) and during the years I've been writing
clients for this radio for different mobile platforms (Maemo, MeeGo,
Harmattan, Windows Phone, BlackBerry 10, Jolla). I love in particular
their "&lt;a href="http://somafm.com/indiepop/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indie Pop Rock&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;" channel that
during these years made me discover some very good artists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When &lt;strong&gt;Spotify&lt;/strong&gt; finally was available in Italy (I'm still using it
right now that I live in the UK), something that I always missed was a
radio with the same good music. Why not just listening to Soma.fm?
Because I like to listen to the music while I commute and in the London
Underground it's nearly impossible to have signal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I was thinking: it would be nice to have &lt;strong&gt;a Spotify playlist with
Soma.fm tracks&lt;/strong&gt;. Wait a moment.... &lt;strong&gt;I can do it!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.andreagrandi.it/images/2015/07/Frankenstein_Jr_Mel_Brooks_1974.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Frankenstein_Jr_Mel_Brooks_1974" src="https://www.andreagrandi.it/images/2015/07/Frankenstein_Jr_Mel_Brooks_1974.jpg" width="60%"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soma.fm publishes the tracks history with all the tracks streamed during
the last hour &lt;a href="http://somafm.com/indiepop/songhistory.html"&gt;http://somafm.com/indiepop/songhistory.html&lt;/a&gt; so I just
needed something to parse this list for me and return me a well
formatted version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="https://import.io"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;import.io&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (it's a service that takes
a web page as input, parse the data and generates a RESTful API to
access this data) I was able to easily get the data I needed. At this
point I only needed to be able to loop through the list, search each
track on Spotify and add it to my playlist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;source code is fully available&lt;/strong&gt; here
&lt;a href="https://github.com/andreagrandi/spotisoma"&gt;https://github.com/andreagrandi/spotisoma&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; you can't just get the code and run it. You will need to get
your own &lt;strong&gt;import.io api key&lt;/strong&gt;, generate your import.io api url, get a
&lt;a href="https://developer.spotify.com/technologies/libspotify/keys/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spotify application
key&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (the
old/deprecated one, since it was nearly impossible for me to use oauth
in a simple Python script due to the fact I didn't have an endpoint to
receive the token back. You can get more informations here:
&lt;a href="https://pyspotify.mopidy.com/en/latest/quickstart/#application-keys"&gt;https://pyspotify.mopidy.com/en/latest/quickstart/#application-keys&lt;/a&gt;)
and set your env variables with your Spotify username and password. Last
but not least: the &lt;strong&gt;old Spotify library&lt;/strong&gt; only works with &lt;strong&gt;Premium&lt;/strong&gt;
accounts.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Andrea Grandi</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2015 10:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2015-07-12:/2015/07/12/soma-fm-spotify-import-io-python-mashup/</guid><category>Python</category><category>import.io</category><category>music</category><category>Python</category><category>soma.fm</category><category>spotify</category></item><item><title>Announcing LastGo: Maemo/MeeGo client for Last.fm</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2010/07/16/announcing-lastgo-maemomeego-client-for-last-fm/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;While I'm still working to
&lt;a href="https://www.andreagrandi.it/2010/07/03/announcing-msoma-maemomeego-client-for-somafm/"&gt;mSoma&lt;/a&gt;
with Lorenzo Bettini, I decided to start writing another application. I
needed to write something from scratch to learn better how to use
&lt;strong&gt;C++&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Qt&lt;/strong&gt; libraries, so I decided to write a client for
&lt;a href="http://www.lastfm.com"&gt;Last.fm&lt;/a&gt; service. The application is still in
full development, but you can already taste it if you have
&lt;strong&gt;extras-devel&lt;/strong&gt; repository enabled on your &lt;strong&gt;N900&lt;/strong&gt;. At the moment it
only supports basic radio features: tuning user's radio, playing a song,
skipping a song and displaying song informations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.andreagrandi.it/images/2010/07/Screenshot-20100716-222755.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.andreagrandi.it/images/2010/07/Screenshot-20100716-222755.png" title="LastGo"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other basic Last.fm features like scrobbling, marking a song as loved or
banned ecc.. are not supported yet, but of course they're planned for
the stable release. Please not that the application is still a bit
unstable even if it works for normal tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a &lt;a href="http://www.lastfm.com"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Last.fm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; subscriber and you
want to test it, please install it from &lt;strong&gt;extras-devel&lt;/strong&gt; repository and
send me your feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; since it's not allowed to use Last.fm API from a mobile phone
(due to API license restrictions) I cannot distribute a valid api key
with the application. I'm writing this software mainly to learn C++ and
Qt and for the future tablets and netbooks that will be based on MeeGo.
If you feel to assume the responsability, you can &lt;a href="http://gitorious.org/lastgo/lastgo/blobs/raw/master/LastGo/apikey.xml"&gt;download the api key
file&lt;/a&gt;
and import it using "Import Api Key" that you can find in the
application menu.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Andrea Grandi</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2010 22:37:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2010-07-16:/2010/07/16/announcing-lastgo-maemomeego-client-for-last-fm/</guid><category>Linux, Maemo (EN), MeeGo, Programmazione, Qt</category><category>client</category><category>last.fm</category><category>music</category><category>N900</category><category>nokia</category></item><item><title>Last.fm: the money music revolution!</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2009/05/11/lastfm-the-money-music-revolution/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="lastfm" src="https://www.andreagrandi.it/images/2009/04/lastfm.jpg" title="lastfm"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non c'è alcun errore nel titolo di questo post. Sebbene lo slogan originale di
&lt;a href="http://www.lastfm.it"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Last.fm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; fosse "&lt;strong&gt;The Social Music
Revolution&lt;/strong&gt;", ho voluto modificarlo in questo modo, per sottolineare il
recente cambiamento di rotta di un servizio che fino a pochi giorni fa
ritenevo uno dei migliori, se non il migliore, del suo genere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facciamo un passo indietro per spiegare cos'è Last.fm. Si tratta di un
servizio che permette, una volta registrati, di condividere le canzoni
che ascoltiamo (titolo e autore, non il file audio) in modo che si possa
essere messi in contatto con altre persone che ascoltano i nostri gruppi
preferiti oppure di ricevere suggerimenti su gruppi simili a quelli che
ascoltiamo. Grazie a questa funzione ho avuto la possibilità di
conoscere ed apprezzare gruppi musicali di cui prima ignoravo
l'esistenza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oltre a permettere lo scrobbling (invio del titolo della canzone) e la
creazione automatica di classifiche, il sito mette a disposizione
moltissimi strumenti che hanno permesso la creazione di una vasta
community musicale. La community, grazie a questi strumenti, ha
arricchito il sito web di moltissimi dati importanti: un wiki con i dati
dei gruppi musicali, i tag su ogni canzone, gruppi di discussione e la
creazione di eventi e ritrovi. Last.fm è anche una "radio", ma in un
modo un po' diverso rispetto a quello a cui siamo abituati.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non esistono playlist valide per tutti gli utenti, ogni utente ha la
propria playlist, in base ai brani ascoltati, ai gruppi simili ed ai
suggerimenti degli amici. Oltre alle proprie playlista è inoltre
possibile ascoltare quelle dei "vicini", degli amici e dei gruppi ai
quali siamo iscritti. Se oggi Last.Fm è diventata quello che tutti
vediamo, è in gran parte grazie al lavoro svolto dalla community
musicale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Che cosa è successo per portarmi alla decisione di &lt;strong&gt;eliminare il mio
account&lt;/strong&gt;, vecchio di &lt;strong&gt;3 anni&lt;/strong&gt;, con piu' di &lt;strong&gt;30.000&lt;/strong&gt; brani
ascoltati?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circa un mese fa i vertici di Last.fm hanno deciso che entro poco tempo
il servizio di radio in streaming sarebbee diventato a pagamento, a
causa dell'aumento dei costi di licenza imposti dalle major. Per
continuare ad ascoltare la radio &lt;strong&gt;si dovranno pagare 3€ al mese&lt;/strong&gt;.
Quello che ha scatenato l'ira di moltissimi utenti e che mi ha fatto
prendere la decisione di disiscrivermi, è il fatto che &lt;strong&gt;USA&lt;/strong&gt;,
&lt;strong&gt;Inghilterra&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;Germania&lt;/strong&gt; potranno continuare ad usufruire
&lt;strong&gt;gratuitamente&lt;/strong&gt; del servizio. Questa divisione in paesi di serie A e
paesi di serie B non è piaciuta proprio a nessuno, basta guardare le
&lt;a href="http://blog.last.fm/2009/04/22/radio-subscriptions"&gt;centinaia di commenti&lt;/a&gt; che sono
arrivati sul blog ufficiale di Last.fm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Io mi associo al pensiero comune: se anche USA, Inghilterra e Germania
pagassero, il costo potrebbe scendere a 1 o 2 euro al mese ed inoltre
non ci sarebbero divisioni e/o discriminazioni a seconda del paese di
provenienza. Avrei pagato volentier anche &lt;strong&gt;3€/mese&lt;/strong&gt; se non ci fossero
state queste differenze. Perchè gli altri paesi devono pagare pochi
privilegiati?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mio parere Last.fm ha commesso un gravissimo errore facendo questa
mossa e sono convinto che entro breve perderà moltissimi utenti
smettendo inoltre di essere una community ricca di contenuti creati
dagli utenti stessi. Staremo a vedere se ci saranno inversioni di rotta
o se continueranno a seguire questa strada.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Andrea Grandi</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2009 19:49:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2009-05-11:/2009/05/11/lastfm-the-money-music-revolution/</guid><category>Recensione</category><category>community</category><category>last.fm</category><category>music</category><category>radio</category><category>streaming</category></item></channel></rss>