<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Andrea Grandi - N900</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/</link><description>Software Developer</description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 13:06:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Maemo Coding Competition: voting open!</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2010/07/26/maemo-coding-competition-voting-open/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is Maemo Coding Competition?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This competition has been organized by Maemo Community for the Maemo
Community. Developer can work to an application and submit it for one of
the six categories available: Desktop, System &amp;amp; Utilities, Games,
Graphics &amp;amp; Multimedia, Location &amp;amp; Navigation, Other. Another category is
available too, and it's for beginner developers. The competition entry
has now ended, but voting is open. You can find more information about
the competition, in the official wiki page:
&lt;a href="http://wiki.maemo.org/Maemo_Coding_Competition_1"&gt;http://wiki.maemo.org/Maemo_Coding_Competition_1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can I vote?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voting is available using a forum's poll for each category. Every t.m.o.
user can give one vote for each category. Here's the complete list of
polls:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Desktop: &lt;a href="http://talk.maemo.org/showthread.php?p=760304"&gt;http://talk.maemo.org/showthread.php?p=760304&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System &amp;amp; Utilities: &lt;a href="http://talk.maemo.org/showthread.php?p=764039"&gt;http://talk.maemo.org/showthread.php?p=764039&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Games: &lt;a href="http://talk.maemo.org/showthread.php?t=58990"&gt;http://talk.maemo.org/showthread.php?t=58990&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graphics &amp;amp; Multimedia:
    &lt;a href="http://talk.maemo.org/showthread.php?p=763679"&gt;http://talk.maemo.org/showthread.php?p=763679&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Location &amp;amp; Navigation:
    &lt;a href="http://talk.maemo.org/showthread.php?t=58964"&gt;http://talk.maemo.org/showthread.php?t=58964&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other: &lt;a href="http://talk.maemo.org/showthread.php?t=59038"&gt;http://talk.maemo.org/showthread.php?t=59038&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beginners: &lt;a href="http://talk.maemo.org/showthread.php?t=59074"&gt;http://talk.maemo.org/showthread.php?t=59074&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;p.s:&lt;/strong&gt; I partecipate in the &lt;strong&gt;Graphics &amp;amp; Multimedia&lt;/strong&gt; category with
two applications: &lt;a href="http://maemo.org/packages/view/lastgo/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LastGo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="http://maemo.org/packages/view/msoma/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mSoma&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Please at least
test them and let me know what do you think about!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 13:06:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2010-07-26:/2010/07/26/maemo-coding-competition-voting-open/</guid><category>Linux, Maemo (EN), MeeGo, Programmazione, Qt</category><category>contest</category><category>N900</category><category>nokia</category></item><item><title>Announcing LastGo: Maemo/MeeGo client for Last.fm</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2010/07/16/announcing-lastgo-maemomeego-client-for-last-fm/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;While I'm still working to
&lt;a href="http://www.andreagrandi.it/2010/07/03/announcing-msoma-maemomeego-client-for-somafm/"&gt;mSoma&lt;/a&gt;
with Lorenzo Bettini, I decided to start writing another application. I
needed to write something from scratch to learn better how to use
&lt;strong&gt;C++&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Qt&lt;/strong&gt; libraries, so I decided to write a client for
&lt;a href="http://www.lastfm.com"&gt;Last.fm&lt;/a&gt; service. The application is still in
full development, but you can already taste it if you have
&lt;strong&gt;extras-devel&lt;/strong&gt; repository enabled on your &lt;strong&gt;N900&lt;/strong&gt;. At the moment it
only supports basic radio features: tuning user's radio, playing a song,
skipping a song and displaying song informations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.andreagrandi.it/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/Screenshot-20100716-222755.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.andreagrandi.it/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/Screenshot-20100716-222755.png" title="LastGo"&gt;{.aligncenter
.size-full .wp-image-386 width="460"
height="276"}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other basic Last.fm features like scrobbling, marking a song as loved or
banned ecc.. are not supported yet, but of course they're planned for
the stable release. Please not that the application is still a bit
unstable even if it works for normal tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a &lt;a href="http://www.lastfm.com"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Last.fm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; subscriber and you
want to test it, please install it from &lt;strong&gt;extras-devel&lt;/strong&gt; repository and
send me your feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; since it's not allowed to use Last.fm API from a mobile phone
(due to API license restrictions) I cannot distribute a valid api key
with the application. I'm writing this software mainly to learn C++ and
Qt and for the future tablets and netbooks that will be based on MeeGo.
If you feel to assume the responsability, you can &lt;a href="http://gitorious.org/lastgo/lastgo/blobs/raw/master/LastGo/apikey.xml"&gt;download the api key
file&lt;/a&gt;
and import it using "Import Api Key" that you can find in the
application menu.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2010 22:37:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2010-07-16:/2010/07/16/announcing-lastgo-maemomeego-client-for-last-fm/</guid><category>Linux, Maemo (EN), MeeGo, Programmazione, Qt</category><category>client</category><category>last.fm</category><category>music</category><category>N900</category><category>nokia</category></item><item><title>Announcing mSoma: Maemo/MeeGo client for SomaFM</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2010/07/03/announcing-msoma-maemomeego-client-for-somafm/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://somafm.com"&gt;SomaFM&lt;/a&gt; is a streaming radio with near 16 different
channels, available for free. Even if it's possible to copy-paste their
streaming URLs to N900 Media Player, we
(&lt;a href="http://maemo.org/profile/view/andy80"&gt;me&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://maemo.org/profile/view/lorebett"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lorenzo
Bettini&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) decided to create a
custom application, to make channels switching easier for the end user
and to be able to add more features. We decided to take advantage of the
new &lt;strong&gt;Nokia SDK&lt;/strong&gt; and write the application in Qt/C++. Source code is
available on &lt;a href="http://gitorious.org/msoma"&gt;Gitorious&lt;/a&gt; and it's always
updated with latest version we're working on. If someone want to test
the application, it's available in &lt;strong&gt;extras-devel&lt;/strong&gt; repository  ("msoma"
under Multimedia section) of N900.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_380" align="aligncenter" width="389"
caption="mSoma"]&lt;a href="http://www.andreagrandi.it/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/msoma_0.1.2.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.andreagrandi.it/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/msoma_0.1.2.png" title="msoma_0.1.2"&gt;{.size-full
.wp-image-380 width="389"
height="233"}&lt;/a&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UI is still in development as you can see. The application is
already usable, but of course we have to work hard on the user
interface. Feel free to test/use it and send us any feedback. If you
want to contribute to our project (coders are welcome) please send us a
patch with your code or ask us to be added to mSoma development team in
Gitorious.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jul 2010 16:31:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2010-07-03:/2010/07/03/announcing-msoma-maemomeego-client-for-somafm/</guid><category>Linux, Maemo (EN), MeeGo, Qt, Recensione</category><category>maemo</category><category>MeeGo</category><category>N900</category><category>nokia</category><category>Qt</category><category>SomaFM</category></item><item><title>Twitter client for Maemo in Qt + Python: call for developers and UI designers</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2010/02/22/twitter-client-for-maemo-in-qt-python-call-for-developers-and-ui-designers/</link><description>&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name's &lt;strong&gt;Andrea Grandi&lt;/strong&gt;, I'm italian and I'm a Maemo
user/lover/contributor since the &lt;strong&gt;Nokia 770&lt;/strong&gt;. I love &lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt; as
development language and few months ago I also gave some contributions
to the &lt;a href="http://pymaemo.garage.maemo.org/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PyMaemo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these days I had the idea to start writing a &lt;strong&gt;Twitter&lt;/strong&gt; client for
&lt;strong&gt;Maemo&lt;/strong&gt; with a precise direction in my mind. I'll try to explain all
my reasons here. First of all I've to thank the author of
&lt;a href="http://mauku.henrikhedberg.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mauku&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; client. I use it since its
first version and I'm quite happy with it. Then, why do I want to write
another one?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maemo&lt;/strong&gt; (MeeGo) is moving to &lt;strong&gt;Qt&lt;/strong&gt; and for this reason I'm going
    to use Qt, while Mauku uses Gtk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm learning Qt and what is better than writing a complete (but not
    too complex) application to learn better?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mauku is not free as lot of people could think. Reading the source
    codeyou find this "You are NOT allowed to modify or redistribute the
    source code.", while I want to write a client and release it under
    &lt;strong&gt;GPL2&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;GPL3&lt;/strong&gt; license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mauku is not updated since some months and we have no news about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I love Python and I like to write free software in this language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to give to Maemo a stronger contribute.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My request for help&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before lot of people start writing their own client resulting in 4-5
twitter clients for Maemo, why don't we join our strength and work to a
common project? I'm not a Python expert nor a Qt one, but I've some
experience as project/team leader and since this is not a complex
project, I would be glad to lead it. So, I'm looking for Python
developers, Qt developers, UI designers and whoever want to contribute
to this project. I still have to find a good name and logo for this
application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who want to help me?&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2010 17:16:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2010-02-22:/2010/02/22/twitter-client-for-maemo-in-qt-python-call-for-developers-and-ui-designers/</guid><category>Linux, Maemo (EN), MeeGo, Programmazione, Python, Qt</category><category>maemo</category><category>MeeGo</category><category>N900</category><category>nokia</category><category>Python</category><category>Qt</category><category>twitter</category></item><item><title>Nokia N900: reboot loop after PR 1.1.1 upgrade is not a firmware bug</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2010/02/20/nokia-n900-reboot-loop-after-pr-1-1-1-upgrade-is-not-a-firmware-bug/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Few days ago I published &lt;a href="http://www.andreagrandi.it/2010/02/17/nokia-n900-some-problems-with-latest-pr-1-1-1-firmware/"&gt;some
notes&lt;/a&gt;
about my personal experience with &lt;strong&gt;PR 1.1.1&lt;/strong&gt; firmware upgrade in Nokia
&lt;strong&gt;N900&lt;/strong&gt;. In particular my device got an infinite reboot loop after
upgrading the firmware and I had to flash the firmware image from
scratch to fix the problem. Today I was kindly contacted by &lt;strong&gt;Max
Waterman&lt;/strong&gt; (I suppose he works for Nokia) and he explained me what was
the problem. It was caused by a little bug in Harmattan UI demo and they
fixed it (the fix is already available in extras-devel).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No surprise for me: extras-devel contains unstable packages and if user
enables it, he does at his own risk. The most important thing is the
fact that the official firmware without any unstable application doesn't
suffer of this problem at all. The thing that really impressed me so
much (in a positive sense) it's that I was contacted privately by a
Nokia developer apologizing for the bug (no problem man, it's part of
the game if someone want to test extras-devel software) and explaining
that they already fixed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what I like of Maemo (or should I already call it MeeGo?), I
really feel to be a part of it!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2010 02:50:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2010-02-20:/2010/02/20/nokia-n900-reboot-loop-after-pr-1-1-1-upgrade-is-not-a-firmware-bug/</guid><category>Linux, Maemo (EN), MeeGo</category><category>firmware</category><category>maemo</category><category>MeeGo</category><category>N900</category><category>nokia</category></item><item><title>Nokia N900: some problems with latest PR 1.1.1 firmware</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2010/02/17/nokia-n900-some-problems-with-latest-pr-1-1-1-firmware/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I don't know if it's just a case or if I'm the only one who had these
problems, but I'll report them anyway, maybe somebody had my same
problem and we could try to prepare a proper bug report to make the
Maemo team fix them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Infinite boot loop after upgrade&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all I have to say that before upgrading to PR 1.1.1 I checked
if I had enough space on the rootfs. I only had 27 Mb and so I decided
to remove some unused applications, deleted some *.deb in
/var/cache/apt/archives and disabled extras repositories. Of course I
also did a backup of all my configuration. After the cleaning operation
I had near 60 Mb free on rootfs, enough to install the upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I closed all running applications, started the application manager and
began the upgrade. After the upgrade was completed, the device did a
reboot... then another one, then again, again.... until I had to remove
the battery to stop it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: I had to re-flash the device with the latest image to make
it work again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;mafw-dbus-wrapper taking all the CPU&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was watching a video (using subtitles) and after some minutes the
whole UI became unresponsive. Strange because I already did this before
without having any problem. I tried to check the problem using "top"
utility from terminal and I saw that there was a mafw process
(mafw-dbus-wrapper) that was taking 80-90% of CPU. My fault is that
normally there are at least 3-4 , mafw-dbus-wrapper processes and I
didn't check which one was causing the problem. Anyway I made a
screenshot, just in case it can help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.andreagrandi.it/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/Screenshot-20100217-034958.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.andreagrandi.it/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/Screenshot-20100217-034958-300x180.png" title="Screenshot-20100217-034958"&gt;{.size-medium
.wp-image-362 .aligncenter width="300"
height="180"}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this short report can be useful to help Maemo team to fix or at
least investigate what happened. Just leave a comment or contact me if
you need more informations.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2010 13:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2010-02-17:/2010/02/17/nokia-n900-some-problems-with-latest-pr-1-1-1-firmware/</guid><category>Linux, Maemo (EN), Recensione</category><category>bug</category><category>firmware</category><category>maemo</category><category>N900</category><category>nokia</category></item><item><title>Questions/Answers about Nokia N900 and Discounted Device Program</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2009/11/12/questionsanswers-about-nokia-n900-and-discounted-device-program/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Being one of the developers who received the discount to buy a N900,
during these days I contacted the DDP customer care to have more
informations and details. I'll publish here both my original question
and the official reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) The price of N900 is 250€ and I've read of people who paid it this
price. Anyway here you say that the VAT is not included:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://pro.forum.nokia.com/site/global/tech_resources/discounted_devices/l_ddp.jsp"&gt;https://pro.forum.nokia.com/site/global/tech_resources/discounted_devices/l_ddp.jsp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
so it should costs 300€ not 250€, right?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The VAT applies only for Finnish developers, for the others the price is
the price they see in the eStore, no VAT is added to that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So, all non-finnish european people, will pay &lt;strong&gt;250€&lt;/strong&gt; for the N900.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) How much time can I wait before ordering it? In this moment I'm in
Valencia (Spain) and I won't come back to Italy before Christmas. I'd
like the order to be shipped to my home in Italy (I registered as
italian user and I want italian keyboard layout), but I'd like to wait
to order it, because since there's no warranty and I need to tell you
about any problem within a week, if I order it now I will be able to
check it only at the end of december when I'll come back to Italy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess this should not be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This part is not confirmed yet, since Quim told us to hurry up to buy
it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3) How many devices can I buy at that price? Here you say I can
buy two:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://pro.forum.nokia.com/site/global/tech_resources/discounted_devices/l_ddp.jsp"&gt;https://pro.forum.nokia.com/site/global/tech_resources/discounted_devices/l_ddp.jsp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
but here you say I can buy one:
&lt;a href="https://pro.forum.nokia.com/showProduct.do?product_id=5096"&gt;https://pro.forum.nokia.com/showProduct.do?product_id=5096&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want two devices, but another friend of mine, who help me in a
project for the Maemo Community, would like to be able to buy one for
the same price (he wasn't able to get the discount because his karma is
still low).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I know, you can only purchase 1x device per person, regarding
MAEMO N900.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4) Where can we find the new firmware? In the FAQ you say: DDP does
not flash devices. It's ok, I can do it, but there's no public firmware
for N900 at the moment.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To update N900, can possibly be using NSU. Nokia software updater.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5) Is it possible to have a device with localized keyboard (for
example italian one) ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All N900 will have EURO variant, Italian language is one option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; even these replies come from the official customer care, I
don't assume any responsability if they shouldn't be all exact. If you
have any doubt, please contact them directly at
&lt;strong&gt;[DDP.program@nokia.com]{}&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">admin</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2009 15:05:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2009-11-12:/2009/11/12/questionsanswers-about-nokia-n900-and-discounted-device-program/</guid><category>Maemo (EN)</category><category>DDP</category><category>discount</category><category>maemo</category><category>N900</category><category>nokia</category></item></channel></rss>