<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Andrea Grandi - Ubuntu (EN)</title><link href="https://andreagrandi.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://andreagrandi.github.io/feeds/ubuntu-en.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://andreagrandi.github.io/</id><updated>2012-08-17T12:28:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Ubuntu Release Sprint: calling for feedback!</title><link href="https://andreagrandi.github.io/2012/08/17/ubuntu-release-sprint-calling-for-feedback/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-08-17T12:28:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-08-17T12:28:00+01:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:andreagrandi.github.io,2012-08-17:/2012/08/17/ubuntu-release-sprint-calling-for-feedback/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;During the last UDS party, I had an idea to improve Ubuntu development,
but I didn't know if it could be a good idea or a stupid one, so I
talked to &lt;strong&gt;Daniel Holbach&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;David Planella&lt;/strong&gt; about it and they
were happy to hear about it and Daniel told …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During the last UDS party, I had an idea to improve Ubuntu development,
but I didn't know if it could be a good idea or a stupid one, so I
talked to &lt;strong&gt;Daniel Holbach&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;David Planella&lt;/strong&gt; about it and they
were happy to hear about it and Daniel told me to talk about
this directly to &lt;strong&gt;Mark&lt;/strong&gt; (and I did it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's explain the basic idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From an UDS and the next one, it would be useful to have a
development sprint where people can talk about assigned UDS blueprints,
at which point they are on their tasks, if they have any problems and if
they will finish them within the next UDS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course Canonical cannot organize another meeting, it would be
very expensive, so the idea is: why don't we use &lt;strong&gt;Google Hangout&lt;/strong&gt; to
organize the sprint? I has a limit of 10 people, I know, but we could
select (for example) 5 from the community and 5 from Canonical. There
would be parallel meeting and tracks, we would use the same blueprints
used during the last UDS and we would add further notes. The
attendees would be able to listen and watch the stream and make
questions through the available chat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also created a &lt;strong&gt;wiki&lt;/strong&gt; page with more informations and you can
find it here: &lt;a href="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/UbuntuReleaseSprint"&gt;https://wiki.ubuntu.com/UbuntuReleaseSprint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think about? I know that Canonical is already
organizing sprints and this could be a way to involve more the Ubuntu
Community. Maybe we should schedule a session &lt;strong&gt;at next UDS&lt;/strong&gt; to talk
about this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to get some &lt;strong&gt;feedback&lt;/strong&gt; from you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="development"></category><category term="meeting"></category><category term="sprint"></category><category term="Ubuntu"></category><category term="UDS"></category></entry><entry><title>Ubuntu Release Sprint: a proposal to improve Ubuntu development</title><link href="https://andreagrandi.github.io/2012/05/12/ubuntu-release-sprint-a-proposal-to-improve-ubuntu-development/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-05-12T22:47:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-05-12T22:47:00+01:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:andreagrandi.github.io,2012-05-12:/2012/05/12/ubuntu-release-sprint-a-proposal-to-improve-ubuntu-development/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, during the final UDS party, I had an idea to improve Ubuntu
development, but I didn't know if it could be a good idea or a stupid
one, so I talked to &lt;strong&gt;Daniel Holbach&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;David Planella&lt;/strong&gt; about it
and they were happy to hear about it and Daniel …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, during the final UDS party, I had an idea to improve Ubuntu
development, but I didn't know if it could be a good idea or a stupid
one, so I talked to &lt;strong&gt;Daniel Holbach&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;David Planella&lt;/strong&gt; about it
and they were happy to hear about it and Daniel told me to talk about
this directly to Mark (and I did it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's explain the basic idea. From an UDS and the next one, it would be
useful to have a development sprint where people can talk about assigned
UDS blueprints, at which point they are on their tasks, if they have any
problems and if they will finish them within the next UDS. Of course
Canonical cannot organize another meeting, it would be very expensive,
so the idea is: why don't we use Google Hangout to organize the sprint?
I has a limit of 10 people, I know, but we could select (for example) 5
from the community and 5 from Canonical. There would be parallel meeting
and tracks, we would use the same blueprints used during the last UDS
and we would add further notes. The attendees would be able to listen
and watch the stream and make questions through the available chat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want to write more details here because I don't think it's the
right place (and probably it's not the moment to write a similar blog
post, since I'm still in th SFO Airport), my idea is to create a wiki
page to explain all the details, so everyone would be able to add more
ideas and see if it's doable or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what do you think about? I think we should try, it doesn't cost
anything except some hours in the week we'll organize it. I wait for
your comments then.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Some ideas to improve Community collaboration for Ubuntu Developer Summit</title><link href="https://andreagrandi.github.io/2011/04/09/some-ideas-to-improve-community-collaboration-for-ubuntu-developer-summit/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-04-09T19:33:00+01:00</published><updated>2011-04-09T19:33:00+01:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:andreagrandi.github.io,2011-04-09:/2011/04/09/some-ideas-to-improve-community-collaboration-for-ubuntu-developer-summit/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.andreagrandi.it/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Ubuntu-Developer-Summit.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.andreagrandi.it/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Ubuntu-Developer-Summit-300x229.png" title="Ubuntu Developer Summit"&gt;{.alignright
.size-medium .wp-image-481
width="200"}&lt;/a&gt;Few
days ago I received an email from &lt;strong&gt;Jorge O. Castro&lt;/strong&gt; of the Ubuntu
Community, announcing me that my request of sponsorization for &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://uds.ubuntu.com/"&gt;Ubuntu
Developer Summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; has been accepted. I have
never attended an UDS before, so I must admit I feel a bit disoriented …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.andreagrandi.it/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Ubuntu-Developer-Summit.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.andreagrandi.it/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Ubuntu-Developer-Summit-300x229.png" title="Ubuntu Developer Summit"&gt;{.alignright
.size-medium .wp-image-481
width="200"}&lt;/a&gt;Few
days ago I received an email from &lt;strong&gt;Jorge O. Castro&lt;/strong&gt; of the Ubuntu
Community, announcing me that my request of sponsorization for &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://uds.ubuntu.com/"&gt;Ubuntu
Developer Summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; has been accepted. I have
never attended an UDS before, so I must admit I feel a bit disoriented
at the moment and maybe I'm missing some important informations, but at
least I'm a good test for the situation of a community member
approaching it for the first time. Since I would like to actively help
the organization of the Summit, I started looking for the right place to
do it. I've a good experience about events organization and during these
years I helped, for example, in the organization of &lt;strong&gt;Maemo Summit&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;MeeGo Conference&lt;/strong&gt;, so I'd like to share my experience with the Ubuntu
Community too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;USD Website&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ubuntu Developer Summit website is &lt;a href="http://uds.ubuntu.com/"&gt;http://uds.ubuntu.com/&lt;/a&gt;. It
looks nice at first view, but it's missing a lot of important
informations and it contains some errors. The
&lt;a href="http://uds.ubuntu.com/travel/"&gt;Travel&lt;/a&gt; section, for example should
be named "Travel and Accomodation" and should contains not only
information about the main hotel where the Summit will take place, but
also useful informations about cheap hotels/hostels for Community people
who are not sponsored. The &lt;a href="http://uds.ubuntu.com/tracks/"&gt;Tracks&lt;/a&gt;
section is still empty. Is it possible that when less than 1 month is
missing, official tracks are not available yet? I don't mean categories,
I mean tracks inside them. The Schedule is still empty too. Clicking any
track take to a page containing an error: I would like to submit this
bug, but where? Even worse, clicking on Schedule takes the visitor to a
different website and there is no ways to navigate back (except clicking
the back button on browser).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Forum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn't able to find any section in the &lt;a href="http://ubuntuforums.org/"&gt;official Ubuntu
forum&lt;/a&gt; where to talk about Ubuntu Developer
Summit. I think it would be useful to have a dedicated section to talk
about UDS or about generic Ubuntu related events. It would be useful for
people to be able to meet/know each other before attending. I was lucky
to meet Marco Trevisan, from the Ubuntu Italian Community, so we will
travel together (thanks to a Twitter message I sent!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;IRC&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;#ubuntu-uds&lt;/strong&gt; channel on &lt;strong&gt;FreeNode&lt;/strong&gt; is not much populated and a
couple of times I visited it nobody wrote anything. We should keep at
least 2-3 people, in turns, always available to answer any question
about UDS, it would be easier for people to find the informations they
look for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wiki&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be nice to have a page on the wiki to organize better the
event. We could write a list of tasks to do and each Community member
could pick one and help with it. In this way we could divide the jobs. I
know there is a lot to do when we organize these kind of events and the
help of the Community is something we cannot risk to miss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Media&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should give some informations to people who will attend UDS to be
sure they will use proper tags when they will publish pictures, tweets,
blog entries ecc... Do we have a tag to use on Flickr? What is the right
tag to use on Twitter? What keywords should we use when we will blog
about the Summit? All these informations are important if we want to be
sure other people will find our posts in an easy way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Mailing List&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu has a lot of &lt;a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/"&gt;mailing lists&lt;/a&gt;, but it
looks like none dedicated to events discussion. There is one called
&lt;a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/Ubuntu-event-planners"&gt;ubuntu-events-planners&lt;/a&gt;
but nobody is using it since months ago. We should use a mailing list to
discuss about events organization and/or create a dedicated one for UDS.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>