<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Andrea Grandi - UDS</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/</link><description>Software Developer</description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2013 01:09:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>UDS happening online only: pros and cons</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2013/03/05/uds-happening-online-only-pros-and-cons/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When last week &lt;a href="http://fridge.ubuntu.com/2013/02/26/ubuntu-developer-summits-now-online-and-every-three-months/"&gt;Canonical announced&lt;/a&gt;
the usual UDS was not going to happen I was a bit shocked and
disappointed: starting from the next UDS (that is going to happen
tomorrow!) the event will be &lt;strong&gt;online only&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;every 3 months&lt;/strong&gt;.
During these days I've been thinking a lot about this move and I will
tell you what are the pros and cons, in my opinion, followed by some
final thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pros&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having 4 UDS every year, instead of 2, is surely a better thing. I'm a
big fan of Scrum methodology, so I think that &lt;strong&gt;iterating more often is
better&lt;/strong&gt; than iterating less. If there are any mistakes you can correct
them and iterating again before releasing the final product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Potentially &lt;strong&gt;more people can partecipate&lt;/strong&gt; to the event (even the
opposite is true and I will explain why). People won't need to move from
home, travel, pay any expense etc... they just need a computer and a
good Internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's &lt;strong&gt;cheaper for everyone&lt;/strong&gt;: I can just imagine how expensive could be
for Canonical to organize a similar event. Booking a big hotel, paying
travel and expenses to near one houndred of community people. People who
didn't get any sponsorization had to pay all the travel expenses to
attend the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Potentially &lt;strong&gt;less people can partecipate&lt;/strong&gt; to the event. Yes, like I
said before even this sentence is true and I will explain why. First of
all, using Google+ there are at least three countries that will be cut
out: &lt;strong&gt;China&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Thailand&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Vietnam&lt;/strong&gt;. Google+ is not available
in those countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you sure that special people will be able to follow the event? For
example &lt;strong&gt;blind people&lt;/strong&gt; won't be able to chat or to ask question in the
chat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Only 10 people&lt;/strong&gt; will be able to talk. In normal UDS sessions more
people could raise the hand and ask a question or interact with the
track leaders. Who will choose the 10 people with audio+video streaming
rights?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will &lt;strong&gt;completly miss the social aspect&lt;/strong&gt; of the UDS. If you think
this was only a secondary part, please go on. I felt more committed to
work and collaborate with people I met in person than with someone I've
never met before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Announcing an event, even if online, just &lt;strong&gt;one week before&lt;/strong&gt; it
happens. Really? Some people had already taken vacation from work,
booked flights etc... not counting many people that can't take 2 days
off from work just with 1 week notice period. It's also almost
impossible that community members have the time to schedule a blueprint
and be able to discuss about a subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a &lt;strong&gt;cutting costs&lt;/strong&gt; point of view I really can't say anything.
Organizing UDS was surely very expensive for Canonical and nobody can
blame them if they decided to spend those money in a different way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What really concerns me: is UDS still useful? My opinion is that at
least since latest 2 or 3 UDS the presence of the Community was not so
relevant, because I had &lt;strong&gt;the clear sensation that the most important
decisions were made by Canonical before the UDS&lt;/strong&gt; and then there was
just some details tuning. Another proof of my thoughts is the today
announcement: &lt;strong&gt;despite the fact that I 100% agree with Unity switching
to Qt/QML&lt;/strong&gt; (I already proposed this 2 years ago during Budapest UDS,
but nobody listened to me) &lt;strong&gt;I completly disagree with the way the
decision was made&lt;/strong&gt;: not a single involvement or discussion with the
community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would apreaciate &lt;strong&gt;more openness and honesty&lt;/strong&gt; from Canonical. Do you
want to take all the decisions? That's fine, but at least state it
clearly.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Andrea Grandi</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2013 01:09:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2013-03-05:/2013/03/05/uds-happening-online-only-pros-and-cons/</guid><category>Ubuntu (EN), UDS</category><category>Canonical</category><category>community</category><category>Linux</category><category>meeting</category><category>Ubuntu</category><category>UDS</category></item><item><title>Ubuntu Release Sprint: calling for feedback!</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2012/08/17/ubuntu-release-sprint-calling-for-feedback/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;During the last UDS party, I had an idea to improve Ubuntu development,
but I didn't know if it could be a good idea or a stupid one, so I
talked to &lt;strong&gt;Daniel Holbach&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;David Planella&lt;/strong&gt; about it and they
were happy to hear about it and Daniel told me to talk about
this directly to &lt;strong&gt;Mark&lt;/strong&gt; (and I did it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's explain the basic idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From an UDS and the next one, it would be useful to have a
development sprint where people can talk about assigned UDS blueprints,
at which point they are on their tasks, if they have any problems and if
they will finish them within the next UDS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course Canonical cannot organize another meeting, it would be
very expensive, so the idea is: why don't we use &lt;strong&gt;Google Hangout&lt;/strong&gt; to
organize the sprint? I has a limit of 10 people, I know, but we could
select (for example) 5 from the community and 5 from Canonical. There
would be parallel meeting and tracks, we would use the same blueprints
used during the last UDS and we would add further notes. The
attendees would be able to listen and watch the stream and make
questions through the available chat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also created a &lt;strong&gt;wiki&lt;/strong&gt; page with more informations and you can
find it here: &lt;a href="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/UbuntuReleaseSprint"&gt;https://wiki.ubuntu.com/UbuntuReleaseSprint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think about? I know that Canonical is already
organizing sprints and this could be a way to involve more the Ubuntu
Community. Maybe we should schedule a session &lt;strong&gt;at next UDS&lt;/strong&gt; to talk
about this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to get some &lt;strong&gt;feedback&lt;/strong&gt; from you.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Andrea Grandi</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2012 12:28:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2012-08-17:/2012/08/17/ubuntu-release-sprint-calling-for-feedback/</guid><category>Ubuntu (EN)</category><category>development</category><category>meeting</category><category>sprint</category><category>Ubuntu</category><category>UDS</category></item><item><title>UDS day-3</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2011/05/11/uds-day-3/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.andreagrandi.it/images/2011/05/IMG_0260-300x200.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even this morning I didn't wake up early because I still felt sick (I already
know this sore throath won't abandon me untile I go back home).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a &lt;strong&gt;light breakfast at 10:30&lt;/strong&gt; and then I finishes uploading some
pictures and published articles on my blog I already had written before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While waiting to attend a session, I found &lt;strong&gt;Mark Shuttleworth&lt;/strong&gt; around
and I congratulated with him for the effort he is putting into Ubuntu.
Without a similar distribution, I'm pretty sure that Linux would not be
so popular today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had lunch at 13:00 as usual and after that I attended a couple of
presentation. The first one on Eucalyptus, then "&lt;strong&gt;Cooking Recipes&lt;/strong&gt;"
for Ubuntu and another one dedicated to &lt;strong&gt;Wine&lt;/strong&gt;. The Wine session was
so funny! They had a little problem with video projector and all the
images appeared with a blur effect so that you could think to be drunk
;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After these sessions I had to go back to my room since I didn't feel
very well, but I was able to attend "&lt;strong&gt;Unity's relations and
dependancies on GNOME&lt;/strong&gt;" thanks to audio streaming, IRC for asking
questions and etherpad to take notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I attended also "&lt;strong&gt;desktop-dx-o-unity-a11y&lt;/strong&gt;" where there was a
discussion about the state of &lt;strong&gt;Unity&lt;/strong&gt; and what can be improved before
&lt;strong&gt;Oneiric&lt;/strong&gt; release. Lot of work has to be done yet, in particular about
accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last session of this day, a
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://summit.ubuntu.com/uds-o/meeting/other-o-sabdfl-community-qa/"&gt;Q+A&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
with &lt;strong&gt;Mark Shuttleworth&lt;/strong&gt;. The session was very interesting! He replied
to all questions coming from the public and from IRC.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Andrea Grandi</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2011 18:24:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2011-05-11:/2011/05/11/uds-day-3/</guid><category>Linux, Ubuntu (EN), UDS</category><category>Budapest</category><category>Developer</category><category>Linux</category><category>summit</category><category>Ubuntu</category><category>UDS</category><category>UDS-O</category></item><item><title>UDS day-2</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2011/05/11/uds-day-2/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.andreagrandi.it/images/2011/05/IMG_0323-300x200.jpg" title="IMG_0323"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This day at UDS started a bit late for me, since i woke up pretty sick (damn
air conditioned!!!). I did not follow any conferences in the morning. I
relly wanted to follow the &lt;strong&gt;Wayland&lt;/strong&gt; one, but when I arrived the room
was already full and it was almost impossible to enter, so I decided not
to enter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I attended "&lt;strong&gt;What's wrong with UDS and how we can fix it&lt;/strong&gt;" session
before having lunch. We discussed the possibility to improve all the
session in general, for example giving them a proper order so that a
team can first discuss some API interface, then another team can discuss
how to design them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had another wonderful and tasty &lt;strong&gt;lunch&lt;/strong&gt;, even if I didn't eat so
much, but food was very good anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the afternoon I followed an interesting track: "&lt;strong&gt;Recommend music
based on current song playing or on users media library&lt;/strong&gt;". We discussed
the possibilities to implement a music suggestion service, based on
user's tastes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent the rest of theconference time writing these blog posts and
uploading pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the sessions we had the &lt;strong&gt;Linaro Showcase&lt;/strong&gt;: lot of demo running
on Linaro and ARM processors. I was really impressed by a robot with
Kinect that was able to follow people recognizing their faces. During
the showcase there was a very nice dinner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After dinner I went out with my friend &lt;strong&gt;Manrique Lopez&lt;/strong&gt; who is here in
Budapest for another conference, so we decided to meet for a good beer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before coming back to the hotel me, &lt;strong&gt;Marco Trevisan&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Andrea
Azzarone&lt;/strong&gt; had a nice talk with &lt;strong&gt;Jorge Castro&lt;/strong&gt;. He really make us feel
part of the Ubuntu family!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Andrea Grandi</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2011 11:20:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2011-05-11:/2011/05/11/uds-day-2/</guid><category>Ubuntu (EN), UDS</category><category>Budapest</category><category>summit</category><category>Ubuntu</category><category>UDS</category><category>UDS-O</category></item><item><title>UDS day-1</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2011/05/11/uds-day-1/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.andreagrandi.it/images/2011/05/IMG_0286-300x200.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My day started at 7:30 with a &lt;strong&gt;very nice breakfast!&lt;/strong&gt; I was alone with
just another guy this morning, in a very big breakbast room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After it I grabbed my badge to avoid queue later and went back to my
room to wake up &lt;strong&gt;Marco Trevisan&lt;/strong&gt; (he was still sleeping :P ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The keynote was opened by &lt;strong&gt;Jono Bacon&lt;/strong&gt; (the Ubuntu Community manager),
followed by Ubuntu founder &lt;strong&gt;Mark Shuttleworth&lt;/strong&gt;. The most interesting
(and tweeted) part of the keynote was "&lt;strong&gt;how to prounounce Oneiric&lt;/strong&gt;"
(Oeniric will be the next Ubuntu release).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The keynote finished with a bit late, so all the other tracks were
shifted forward. I followed "&lt;strong&gt;Unity 2D Oneiric Improvements&lt;/strong&gt;", it was
interesting because there were some &lt;strong&gt;Nokia/Qt&lt;/strong&gt; guys and they looked
very interested in helping the Unity 2D team and collaborating with
them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now following "&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/DocumentationTeam/SystemDocumentation/Tasks/Oneiric"&gt;Shaping a strategy for Ubuntu user assistance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;",
I just had the possibility my involvement into helping people that
require Ubuntu assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;lunch&lt;/strong&gt; has been very tasty, I had the possibility to eat some
local recipes, not bad at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After lunch we had a short session on &lt;strong&gt;Qt&lt;/strong&gt;. The version 4.8 is going
to be released in a couple of months, while 5.0 is announced to be
released in 1 year from now: it will be almost code-compatible with 4.x,
it will have an improved support for Qt Quick and QML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As last track of the day I decided to follow "&lt;strong&gt;Personal Cloud&lt;/strong&gt;". Not a
perfect track, since the person who should have been here was only
talking with us using Skype and it was more difficoult to hear what he
said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of this day there was the "&lt;strong&gt;Meet &amp;amp; Greet&lt;/strong&gt;" party, sponsored
by Freescale and Openstack. They offered a dinner and we had some good
music after it.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Andrea Grandi</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2011 11:05:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2011-05-11:/2011/05/11/uds-day-1/</guid><category>Ubuntu (EN), UDS</category><category>Budapest</category><category>Canonical</category><category>conference</category><category>Ubuntu</category><category>UDS</category></item><item><title>UDS day-0</title><link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/2011/05/11/uds-day-0/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.andreagrandi.it/images/2011/05/IMG_0254-300x200.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I left from &lt;strong&gt;Firenze&lt;/strong&gt; with my friend &lt;strong&gt;Marco Trevisan&lt;/strong&gt;, to go to
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://uds.ubuntu.com"&gt;Ubuntu Developer Summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;Budapest&lt;/strong&gt;. We
changed flight in &lt;strong&gt;Rome&lt;/strong&gt; where we met also &lt;strong&gt;Andrea Azzarone&lt;/strong&gt;.
Unluckly &lt;strong&gt;Alitalia losts Marco's baggage&lt;/strong&gt;, so he's still waiting for
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrived at the hotel at 20:00 more or less where we met other people
of the community. There are &lt;strong&gt;lot of italians&lt;/strong&gt; at UDS. Most work for
Canonical, other were sponsored by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I met &lt;strong&gt;Marianna Raffaele&lt;/strong&gt; (one of the UDS organizer... yeah, she's
italian too!), I had to explain her a little problem I had with my
booking (nothing bad) and she managed to help me. She also gave me a
very nice guitar plettre with Ubuntu logo. Thank you Marianna for this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We went out with &lt;strong&gt;Jorge Castro&lt;/strong&gt; to drink some beers (he offered me
one, thanks Jorge!!!) and we met lot of other Ubuntu people. A really
amazing start!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Andrea Grandi</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2011 10:40:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.andreagrandi.it,2011-05-11:/2011/05/11/uds-day-0/</guid><category>Ubuntu (EN), UDS</category><category>Budapest</category><category>conference</category><category>summit</category><category>Ubuntu</category><category>UDS</category></item></channel></rss>