<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Hackathon on Andrea Grandi</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/tags/hackathon/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Hackathon on Andrea Grandi</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.andreagrandi.it/tags/hackathon/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>AI won’t take your Software Developer job (not yet)</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/ai-wont-take-your-job-yet/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/ai-wont-take-your-job-yet/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/ai-wont-take-your-job-yet/ai-doing-developers-work-cover.webp" alt="Featured image of post AI won’t take your Software Developer job (not yet)" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the last 3 days I had the opportunity to participate to an internal hackathon organised by the company I work for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had to build a project based on an SDK and the needed skills to build it were those of a frontend developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a backend developer and having very basic (almost none) frontend skills, I was suggested to use ChatGPT to write some of the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;challenge-accepted&#34;&gt;Challenge accepted
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course I accepted and I worked on the project with another colleague (also backend developer) who also used ChatGPT to write some of the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-normally-use-chatgpt&#34;&gt;How I normally use ChatGPT
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;ChatGPT is not new to me. I use it daily for my work, but I mostly use it as a &amp;ldquo;search engine on steroids&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than searching something on a search engine, read a few blog posts or forums, then landing on a Stack Overflow page, to find some code and adapt it, I ask the same question to ChatGPT and then I adapt the produced example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never ask for a complete feature or even a whole method. I usually need a small example for a very specific thing which I then insert in an existing code base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-used-it-for-the-hackathon&#34;&gt;How I used it for the hackathon
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the case of the hackathon, I knew what I wanted to achieve, but I had no idea how to do it, so I asked it to produce almost everything I needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning it was easy: I had nothing and I was adding small pieces every time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a little bit I ended up with a lot of code I couldn&amp;rsquo;t understand anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was having an issue with the produced code and ChatGPT, instead of helping, started to allucinate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of asking it to fix a specific issue, I was passing back the whole JavaScript file, asking for the issues to be corrected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t notice that while fixing the issues, ChatGPT was also rewriting the whole file and in a couple of occasions it started changing the logic entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The errors disappeared but the code started behaving differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end we had to revert to a simpler and older version of our code, which at least was working correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I remain confident that tools like ChatGPT can be valuable assets for software developers, provided they already possess a strong understanding of the relevant domain, such as Python backend development in my experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, for areas outside one&amp;rsquo;s expertise, such as frontend development, relying solely on ChatGPT is insufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is your experience with similar tools? Let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
