<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>C on Andrea Grandi</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/tags/c/</link>
        <description>Recent content in C on Andrea Grandi</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.andreagrandi.it/tags/c/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Writing Python bindings of existing C libraries - (1) - Introduction</title>
        <link>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/writing-python-bindings-of-existing-c-libraries-1-introduction/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.andreagrandi.it/posts/writing-python-bindings-of-existing-c-libraries-1-introduction/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This summer I&amp;rsquo;m having the pleasure of working in
&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.igalia.com&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Igalia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a spanish free software company)
for a couple of months and they assigned me to an interesting project:
developing &lt;strong&gt;Python bindings&lt;/strong&gt; for &lt;strong&gt;MAFW&lt;/strong&gt; library (a &lt;strong&gt;Maemo&lt;/strong&gt;
multimedia library that will be used in &lt;strong&gt;Fremantle&lt;/strong&gt; release).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the opportunity to work both with &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt; (yes, Python bindings are
almost C code) and &lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt; (it&amp;rsquo;s a good practice to write unittest of
all implemented methods) it&amp;rsquo;s a good way to improve my knowledges in
both languages and since I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to find much documentation about
these kind of things, I&amp;rsquo;m going to share my own experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-a-binding&#34;&gt;What is a Binding?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A binding is a Python module, written in C language, that allows Python
developers to call functions from existing C libraries from their python
applications. It&amp;rsquo;s just like a &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;bridge&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; from C world to Python one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-writing-bindings&#34;&gt;Why writing bindings?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of reasons to write python bindings instead of
writing a library in python language from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all I don&amp;rsquo;t think is good duplicating code, so if a library
already exists and it&amp;rsquo;s written in C, why writing it again in another
language? There&amp;rsquo;s no reason. A lot of code already exist in C world and
all we have to do is to create a bridge with python world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another good reason, in particular when a C library doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist yet,
is the fact that python code is slower than C code for some tasks (for
example multimedia codecs). In these cases is good to implement the core
library in C language and then create a python binding for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;coming-next&#34;&gt;Coming next&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the title of this post says, this is only an introduction to the
subjects I&amp;rsquo;m going to write about. If you have any particular request
about any argument you would like to read, please feel free to leave me
a comment. Next posts will talk about these things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A simple example of binding:&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ll write a simple library in C
language and I&amp;rsquo;ll show how to create the relative python binding,
providing complete source code and an example for python developers.```&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building and installing python bindings with distutils:&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ll
explain how to use &lt;strong&gt;distutils&lt;/strong&gt; to build and install the binding
(using the well know method &amp;ldquo;python setup.py install&amp;rdquo;).```&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defining new types:&lt;/strong&gt; this post will be about how to write new
types in C language and being able to use them from python code.```&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using codegen to write bindings:&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ll explain how to use
&lt;strong&gt;codegen&lt;/strong&gt; utils to automate lot of tasks, to generate the most
part of binding code and how to customize the generated code using
overrides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
